<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exposition of the 28. verse of the third chapter of the epistle to the Romans Wherein is manifestly proued the doctrine of iustification by faith, and by faith onely. By Francis Bunny, one of the prebendaries of the Cathedrall Church of Durham.</title>
            <author>Bunny, Francis, 1543-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17247</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4099</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117367</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852581</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852581</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17908</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17247)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17908)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1228:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exposition of the 28. verse of the third chapter of the epistle to the Romans Wherein is manifestly proued the doctrine of iustification by faith, and by faith onely. By Francis Bunny, one of the prebendaries of the Cathedrall Church of Durham.</title>
                  <author>Bunny, Francis, 1543-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32, 43-73, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby, for Henry Fetherstone,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 33-42 missing in number only; text continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans 3, 28 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Justification --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17908:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17908:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXPOSITION OF THE 28. VERSE OF THE THIRD CHAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER OF THE EPISTLE TO THE ROMANS. Wherein is manifeſtly proued the Doctrine of IVSTIFICATION by FAITH, and by Faith onely.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> FRANCIS BVNNY, <hi>one of the Prebendaries</hi> of the Cathedrall Church of DVRHAM.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Habac. 2.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The iuſt ſhall liue by his Faith.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>William Stansby,</hi> for <hi>Henry Fetherſtone.</hi> 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17908:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:17908:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, MY VERY GOOD LORD, <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> LORD BISHOP of DVRHAM, F. B. wiſheth moſt happy increaſe of all graces in this life, and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe happineſſe in the life to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow bad a gueſt ſinne is, and how vnworthy to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertayned in the houſe of our hearts, there is no man but will readily confeſſe, if he conſider, firſt, how di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent it is to ſolicit and allure to euill, alwayes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoking and intiſing to offend; and when it hath preuailed, how clamorous it is and ready to accuſe vs, neuer ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vs to haue true peace and quietneſſe, vntill by ſome meanes or other, we finde our ſelues reconciled to him againſt whom we haue offended. Neither by any other way can this atonement with God be wrought, ſo that our conſciences may without feare ſtand before God,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.25.</note> but by him only whom God hath ſet forth to be <hi>a reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion through faith in his bloud.</hi> He is called <hi>Ieſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe he ſaueth his people from their ſins.</hi> And,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>we haue peace with God through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Now this peace with God, which Chriſt by his death hath wrought, paying for a ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome thereof, his precious bloud, is made to dwell in our hearts, by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17908:3"/> an aſſured faith, and ſtedfaſt apprehenſion of the mercies of God in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But the light of comfort which this moſt ſweet doctrine ſhould make to ſhine to ſuch, as feeling the burden of their ſinne, grone to bee eaſed of the ſame, is ſo dimmed and darkened by the clouds of Merits, and ſuch Satisfactions as men haue deuiſed to blinde the eyes of the ſimple withall, that hardly they can finde that true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. I therefore in two Sermons, preached at Durham, inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured according to my ſmall talent, to ſcatter thoſe miſts, and to make the Sunne of truth to ſhine to all ſuch, as wilfully doe not winke against the ſame. Wherein how little ſoeuer I haue perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, my indeuour was to take away ſome ſtumbling blocks (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the vnlearned haue beene ſomewhat hindered) that the truth might haue free paſſage. This ſhort Treatiſe hath long lyen hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in corners, almoſt quite forgotten, at the leaſt without any pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that I had to publiſh the ſame, vntill a right Worſhipfull friend thinking better thereof, then it was my part to doe, ſhewed himſelfe very forward to furder the publiſhing of it. Seeing therefore it muſt come to light, I humbly intreat your Lordſhip, that it may goe forth vnder the ſhaddow of your protection, who haue most right thereto, not only in reſpect of your Honours diuers fauours ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to my ſelfe, but becauſe the Sermons were (long ſince) preached in your Cathedrall Church, perchance alſo in your owne hearing, at the leaſt by one deuoted to your Lordſhip, who will pray the Father of all graces to inrich your Honour with his heauenly bleſsings, to the comfort of Gods Church, while here you liue, and in the end to your endleſſe and vnſpeakable ioy, in a better life.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in all duety at commandement, FRA. BVNNY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:17908:3"/>
            <head>AN EXPOSITION OF IVSTIFICATION BY FAITH.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 3.28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>We conclude that a man is iuſtified by Faith, without the workes of the Law.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL knowledge of things godly, and neceſſary for this life of ours, is good and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable: but none more needful for a Chriſtian, either yet ſo comfortable for a wounded and afflicted conſcience,<note place="margin">The moſt needfull know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note> as that which teacheth vs, how, and by what meanes, wee may haue peace with God. For when without partiality we take a view of our ſelues, and conſider duly of our owne waies (which thing we muſt doe, before we can haue true quietneſſe at home in our own conſciences, or perfect reconciliation with God) we cannot but ſee in our ſelues many wants and infirmities, often doing the euill we ſhould not, omitting alſo and that not ſeldom, the good duties which we ſhould performe: alwaies wanting that cheerefulneſſe, alacritie, and ſinceritie in the good things we inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour or take in hand, which muſt by Chriſt, ſeaſon our worke, and make it acceptable to God. In regard of ſo manifold imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, how ſhall we be able with confidence and aſſurance, to ſtand before that iuſt Iudge, who alſo ſeeth the very ſecret of our harts, and ſearcheth our hidden thoughts (and therefore before him, euen the leaſt and moſt vnknowne offence lyeth open) vnleſſe we know aſſuredly that our atonement is made?</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul,</hi> as in many other places, ſo in theſe wordes alſo, preacheth vnto vs moſt plainely, the meanes of our atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and how it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe that we are reconciled to God,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17908:4"/> and (as I may ſay) friended with him. But Satan, that ancient ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to mankind,<note place="margin">Satans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to darken this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note> who ſeeketh, and that moſt greedily, the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our body &amp; ſoule, by his inſtruments in the Popiſh Church, indeuoureth to dimme this Sunne-ſhine, that we ſhould not inioy that ſweet comfort: and to put this candle vnder the buſhell of violent and falſe interpretations; leſt the light thereof, ſhining in the houſe of God, ſhould diſcouer the abſurditie of their errors. I therefore will aſſay (as God ſhall inable me) <hi>to put this candle in a candle-ſticke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>that it may giue light to the whole houſe of God,</hi> by free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it from their wreſted gloſſes.</p>
            <p>To come then roundly to the matter, the difference between vs and our aduerſaries concerning theſe words, ſtandeth eſpecially in two points: The one is the interpretation and meaning of the wordes themſelues: for the other, they much miſlike the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (of our iuſtification by Faith only) which out of the wordes we gather. Therefore will I (by Gods aſſiſtance) <hi>firſt,</hi> iuſtifie our expoſition, <hi>then</hi> alſo our concluſion. Which that I may more fully performe, I purpoſe in <hi>the third</hi> place to anſwere the principall obiections that they haue out of Gods word, whereby theſe ſeeke to impugne our doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iuſtifying, what it ſignifieth.</note>And firſt this word of iuſtifying, our aduerſaries following that ſenſe which the Latine word may yeeld, as if <hi>iuſtificare,</hi> to iuſtifie, muſt be to make righteous, doe take it for an inherent righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: as if the Apoſtle had ſaid, By faith we are inabled to liue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily, and to haue increaſe in righteouſneſſe. True it is, I confeſſe, that our gracious God, of his infinite goodneſſe and mercy, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in vs holineſſe alſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 15 9. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.6.</note> and godlineſſe, <hi>Purifying our hearts by Faith, without which it is impoſsible to pleaſe God;</hi> and therefore iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification in that ſenſe, we denie not, but willingly acknowledge it to be an effect of Faith, and that all our goodneſſe groweth from it, as the fruit from the roote, and heat and light from the Sunne: but <hi>the queſtion</hi> which is now to be anſwered, is, how the word <hi>(iuſtified)</hi> muſt here in theſe wordes of <hi>S. Paul</hi> be taken?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.5.</note>I ſay then, it is moſt likely that <hi>S. Paul,</hi> being <hi>of the kindred of Iſrael, of the tribe of Beniamin, an Hebrew of the Hebrewes,</hi> as hee was beſt acquainted with the Hebrew phraſe, ſo he would rather vſe it then the Latine. Nay, this is more then likely, becauſe in this very Chapter before, he hath vſed this very word according to the Hebrew phraſe, and in that ſenſe, that it hath commonly in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17908:4"/> Scripture, as our aduerſaries themſelues muſt needes confeſſe, in his allegation out of the 51. <hi>Pſalme.</hi> It is therefore very abſurd,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.4.</note> that our aduerſaries, to confirme their ſenſe of this word, are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſo to vnderſtand it, as it is neuer, or at the leaſt very ſeldome vnderſtood in the Scripture, ſo that hardly they can alleage any teſtimonies, where of neceſſitie it muſt bee taken in their ſenſe: whereas we are able to bring very many, which they confeſſe muſt haue our ſenſe.</p>
            <p>Another abſurditie I find in their interpretation,<note place="margin">Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded by the Popiſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found theſe two notable benefits which we haue by Chriſt: that is, our iuſtification, &amp; our ſanctification. Of the firſt he ſpeaketh in this place, &amp; to the end of the fift Chap: and of the latter he begins to ſpeake in the ſixt Chap. as (to the end I need not ſtand long in proofe hereof) <hi>Tho.</hi> of <hi>Aquine</hi> (whom, I know, our aduerſaries wil truſt in a greater matter then this is) ſhall teſtifie for vs in theſe wordes: <hi>After the Apoſtle hath ſhewed, that by the grace of Chriſt we are freed from ſinnes paſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tho. Aquin. in Rom. <hi>6.</hi> Lec. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>as well that which hath beene brought in by the firſt man as that which by the Law aboundeth: here he ſheweth, that by the grace of Chriſt, power is giuen vs to reſist ſinne afterward.</hi> And this he teacheth, entring into his expoſition vpon the ſixt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> prouing directly that which I haue ſaid. Now, the confounding of theſe two benefits, which the Apoſtle here and elſe-where diſtinguiſheth, is very abſurd.</p>
            <p>But here by the way I would aske a queſtion of our Romiſh Maſters, what they thinke of theſe wordes of their Angellical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor? For if it be true that he ſaith, as it is indeed moſt true, and well warranted by the Word it ſelfe: then is it moſt falſe that our aduerſaries here ſay, that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of an inherent righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, which I thus proue; Inherent righteouſneſſe is for the auoiding of ſinne to come, but the Apoſtle ſpeaketh not of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiding of ſinne to come, before the beginning of the ſixt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: therefore, before the beginning of the ſixt Chapter, he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not of inherent righteouſneſſe. The <hi>Minor,</hi> which is onely by them to be denyed, is taken out of the words of <hi>Tho. Aquinas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides theſe abſurdities, we haue ſtrong arguments, whereby to refell their interpretation. As firſt,<note place="margin">The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> the intent and meaning of the Apoſtle, who from the 16. verſe of the firſt Chapter, vnto theſe words, proueth, that all both Iewes and Gentiles ſtand in need of the mercy of God, becauſe they are all found guiltie before him.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17908:5"/> The Gentiles not hauing the Law written,<note place="margin">All are ſinners.</note> yet had ſuch light of nature ſhining in their heart, as taught them ſo far forth to know what was good, and what was bad, that <hi>they had their thoughts accuſing one another</hi> when they did euill, <hi>or excuſing,</hi> if they liued according to that knowledge. But they walked not after that light, neither followed that which their owne conſcience told them was good;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 2.15.</note> they ſhewed not in their life <hi>the effect of the Law written in their hearts:</hi> but might ſay with that vnhappy woman MEDEA, <hi>Video meliora probo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, deteriora ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quor: I ſee and approue that which is better, I follow that which is worſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Iewes, among whom were the Lawes of God writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in tables of ſtone, and that they might neuer bee vnmindfull thereof, they had their Prieſts for an ordinarie meane of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, yea the Prophets alſo as Gods extraordinary remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers, to put them in remembrance of their duty, and of Gods Law; they, I ſay, who had greater helps to haue beene better; yet liued ſo little according to that Law, that the Apoſtle thus chargeth them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>The name of God is blaſphemed among the Gentiles for you.</hi> Hereupon the Apoſtle thus concludeth, <hi>That by the works of the Law, ſhall no fleſh be iuſtified in Gods ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 23.</note>But the Apoſtle hauing thus proued, that <hi>all haue ſinned, and are depriued of the glory of God,</hi> will not leaue vs in that vncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table caſe, but ſheweth by and by how we are deliuered. And as he hath taught vs, that all both Iewes, and Gentiles, are tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Law, and by tranſgreſſion guiltie: ſo now moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably he declareth, how we ſhall be acquitted of our tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,<note place="margin">Our deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery from ſinne.</note> that we may plead not guilty. The queſtion then being, how we being breakers of Gods Law, may appeare before our God, and with confidence, and plead not guilty. This we can neuer doe by any inherent righteouſneſſe, no goodneſſe, no holineſſe, that in this vale of miſery, while wee carry about vs this lumpe of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fleſh, wee can attayne vnto, may acquire vs before God, but this muſt be by faith in Ieſus Chriſt, as the Apoſtle teacheth. Now by this it is plaine enough, that the Apoſtle ſaying wee are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Faith, and bringing this as the concluſion of all his former diſcourſe, ſhould ſpeake nothing to the purpoſe, if he would here tell vs how we may liue righteouſly, who muſt rather teach vs how we may be freed from the danger, wherein hee hath proued that all men are.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:17908:5"/>
            <p>And as the Apoſtle had in theſe words no meaning to ſhew how wee are inabled to walke in holineſſe (for of that he meaneth after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to ſpeake, as before I ſhewed) ſo the words themſelues doe ſufficiently confute our aduerſaries, as by this argument may bee proued. The Apoſtle ſpeaketh in theſe words, of ſuch Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as is not gotten or had by workes:<note place="margin">Not by workes.</note> but the Iuſtification in the Popiſh ſence is only by workes, therefore the Popiſh Iuſtification is not that which the Apoſtle mentioneth. The <hi>Maior</hi> is plaine by the words of this text. <hi>A man is iuſtified without workes.</hi> The <hi>Minor</hi> they will not deny. For that increaſe of righteouſneſſe, which our aduerſaries ſo much ſpeake of, is nothing elſe,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> but to <hi>ioyne vertue with faith, and with vertue knowledge, and with knowledge tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and with temperance patience, and with patience godlineſſe, and with godlineſſe brotherly kindneſſe, and with brotherly kindneſſe loue.</hi> Such a continuall labouring to be adorned with all goodneſſe,<note place="margin">Good workes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie.</note> is the Iuſtification, that is by inherent righteouſneſſe. This, I confeſſe, is a goodly ornament vnto a Chriſtian. But if wee looke well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout vs, we ſhall find it too ſhort to couer our imperfections, and therefore muſt wee ſeeke otherwiſe to appeare righteous before God, namely, in the righteouſneſſe of Ieſus Chriſt, by whom wee haue forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. And whereas the Apoſtle denyed that wee are iuſtified by workes, would you not thinke hee ſpoke very abſurdly, to take this word as the Romiſh Church vnderſtandeth it? For to ſay a man is made godly without good workes (and this they muſt ſay) is as if I ſhould affirme, any thing to be burnt in the fire, without heate.</p>
            <p>Againe, Iuſtification in our aduerſaries ſence is alwayes in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. For it is our regeneration or new birth, our renouation or ſanctification, which can neuer bee perfected, ſo long as wee are in this fleſh, and carry about with vs this bodie ſubiect to ſinne. Heere wee are militant and ſtriuing, after, wee muſt looke for the crowne. Heere we are Pilgrimes, after this wee ſhall be Citizens, and reſt in ioy. <hi>For now wee know but in part, wee prophecie in part:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>But when that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part ſhall be aboliſhed.</hi> And as our knowledge is but in part, euen ſo, yea much more is our obedience heere very maimed and vnperfect. That <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe confeſſeth, <hi>Our inward man is renewed daily</hi> (ſayth he.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16.</note>) And hee whoſe prayſe is in the Scripture for wiſdome, doth verie aptly liken, <hi>the way of the righteous to the morning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 4.18.</note> 
               <hi>that ſhineth as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17908:6"/> the light, that ſhineth more and more, vnto the perfect day.</hi> By which fit ſimilitude <hi>Salomon</hi> ſetteth forth vnto vs, the continuall increaſe in godlineſſe, that an inherent righteouſneſſe (that I may ſo terme our maimed and vnperfect obedience) can bring forth. Saint <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> pithily and prettily expreſſeth as much, comparing man in reſpect of his fall, vnto one that falleth vpon a heape of ſtones and in the myre too.<note place="margin">Bernardus de Coena Domini.</note> 
               <hi>Cecidimus ſuper aceruum lapidum</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>&amp; in luto; vnde non ſolum inquinati, ſed etiam vulnerati, &amp; grauiter quaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſati ſumus: lauari quidem cito poſſuinus; ad ſanandum vero opus eſt curatione multa. We haue falne vpon a heape of ſtones and in the mire; ſo as wee are not only defiled, but wounded alſo and ſore bruiſed. Wee may quickly be waſht, but to heale vs there muſt bee long time.</hi> By wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing away our myre, he meaneth our Iuſtification, which he ſaith may ſoone be, but by healing our wounded and bruiſed nature, he vnderſtandeth our ſanctification,<note place="margin">Aug. de Trinit. lib. <hi>14.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> which is long in doing. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt truly, ſayth Saint <hi>Augustine, Sanè renouatio iſta non fit in momento: Truly this renewing or new birth is not wrought of a ſudden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to adde an Aſſumption to that propoſition, that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on already perfited. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.</note> is alreadie in them that are iuſtified: <hi>We are iuſtified</hi> (ſayth hee) as ſpeaking of a thing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie perfited: as alſo elſewhere, <hi>being iuſtified by faith, wee haue peace with God.</hi> The ſame Apoſtle telling the Corinthians, <hi>that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatours, Idolaters, &amp;c. ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God:</hi> &amp; apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this vnto them,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.</note> ſaith, <hi>Such were ſome of you, but you are iuſtified.</hi> Theſe reaſons then being wel conſidered of, giue vs to vnderſtand, that there is ſo great difference betweene that ſence of this word Iuſtification which our aduerſaries would haue, and that which is agreeable to the Apoſtles meaning, as that their expoſition of this word heere, cannot be good and true.</p>
            <p>But as I miſlike (and that iuſtly) of that they teach; ſo is it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful I ſhould ſhew what is the true meaning of this word. We ſeeke no ſtrange ſignification of the word, neyther force it to any other, then that in the Scriptures moſt commonly it hath, and moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belongeth vnto it. This I might proue by infinite teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: I will produce but ſome few. <hi>Hee that iuſtifieth the wicked</hi> (ſayth <hi>Salomon) and hee that condemneth the iuſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 17.15</note> 
               <hi>euen they both are abomination vnto the Lord.</hi> In like ſort in <hi>Eſay,</hi> God by that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet denounceth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>Woe to them that iuſtifie the wicked.</hi> I know, our aduerſaries will not ſay, that woe ſhall be to them that ſhall make
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17908:6"/> a wicked man righteous, and reforme his vngodlineſſe: but to ſuch <hi>as call euill good, or good euill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 5 20.</note> The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth his ſinnes to be verie great, that GODS faithfulneſſe in ſhewing mercie to him, may bee confeſſed, <hi>that thou</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>maiſt be iuſtified in thy ſayings:</hi> which words the Apoſtle in this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Chapter alleadgeth, as before is ſaid. But that God ſtandeth in need to be iuſtified in the Popiſh ſence, our aduerſaries dare not for ſhame ſay. To be ſhort, the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth thus. <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not into iudgement with thy ſeruants, O Lord: for in thy ſight, ſhall no man liuing be iuſtified.</hi> In all which and infinite moe places that I might produce, the word iuſtifying is ſo taken, as that a man is abſolued or acquited, that hee is pronounced not guiltie: and ſo muſt it in theſe words be vnderſtood, when the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>wee are iuſtified by faith,</hi> that is, by faith wee ſtand before GOD, and may plead, not guiltie.</p>
            <p>For confirmation of that which I haue ſaid, I vſe this argument. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh heere of ſuch Iuſtification,<note place="margin">Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth peace. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.</note> as maketh vs to haue peace with God. For ſo are the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Being iuſtifi'd by faith, wee haue peace with God:</hi> But Iuſtification in the Popiſh ſence maketh vs not to haue peace with GOD, and in our ſence it bringeth peace with God: therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh not of Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Popiſh ſence, but in ours. My <hi>Minor</hi> only is to be proued: (for I haue alreadie ſhewed that the Apoſtle auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the <hi>Maior</hi>) and that hath two parts, the one negatiue, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I deny Iuſtification in their ſence to bring peace with God: the other affirmatiue, that in our ſence it doth.</p>
            <p>That Iuſtification, as it is a doing of good workes, and a liuing righteouſly, ſo farre forth as mans frailetie will permit, (which is the ſence that our aduerſaries ſay belongs to this word heere) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not procure our peace with God, I proue, becauſe the perfection of the Law which wee are commanded to obſerue and keepe, is ſuch as man can neuer attaine to the fulfilling thereof.<note place="margin">None can fulfill the Law.</note> For who is hee that can ſo rule his affections by the Spirit, that hee can in all ſincerity and ſoundneſſe ſerue the Lord? Not any Man, but Chriſt, could euer doe it, as the godly moſt plainely confeſſe. The reaſon is, becauſe the Law commandeth perfection, and our weakeneſſe is not able to performe it. The Apoſtle teacheth vs ſo much, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>It was impoſſible for the Law, in as much as it was weake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe of the fleſh, to free vs from the Law of ſinne or of death.</hi> If then our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17908:7"/> obedience be ſo vnperfit, can wee hope to finde quietneſſe in our conſciences, and peace with GOD, when wee ſhall ſtand before him, who becauſe he is infinite in wiſedome, ſeeth all things, bee they done neuer ſo ſecretly or in the darke, yea, hee heareth what we whiſper in the eare, and knoweth the moſt ſecret thoughts of the heart: and becauſe he is iuſt, will puniſh tranſgreſſors, and in that he is Almightie, is able to take vengeance? No, no, our beſt workes can in this caſe giue vs no ſecuritie. Then by inherent righteouſneſſe we haue not peace with God.</p>
            <p>But that knowing our ſelues to bee acquited of our ſinnes, wee haue peace with GOD (and in that ſence wee take this word of iuſtifying) it is moſt plaine.<note place="margin">Sinne hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth our peace with God.</note> For firſt, the thing that hindreth this our peace, is ſinne: ſinne, I ſay, that naughtie and noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome neighbour, euen the worſt neighbour that any man can dwell with. It neuer reſteth but eyther by faire meanes or foule, it intiſeth to conſent to it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23.</note> For what elſe is that Law that <hi>Paul did ſee in his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, rebelling againſt the Law of his mind, and leading him captiue vnto the law of ſinne, which was in his members?</hi> And when it hath preuailed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.3.</note> 
               <hi>it is euer before vs</hi> as a ſeruant of God complaineth, neither will it let vs take any reſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>it lyeth at the doore</hi> of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, alwaies accuſing, and bawling againſt vs. And marke I pray you what ſowre fruit this bitter roote yeeldeth: It maketh a breach betweene God and vs, as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> telleth Gods people in his dayes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 59.2.</note> 
               <hi>Your ſinnes haue ſeparated betweene you and your God, and your iniquities haue hidden his face from you, that hee will not heare.</hi> And by that meanes wee are depriued of many bleſſings, which GOD vſeth to beſtow vpon his ſeruants, as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Prophets alſo ſaith to the Iewes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.25.</note> 
               <hi>Your iniquities haue turned away theſe things</hi> (ſpeaking of raine in due ſeaſon, and the appointed time of harueſt) <hi>and your ſinnes haue hindered good things from you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.</note> And yet by ſinne, wee haue greater hurt then this. For God denounceth many plagues againſt his people if they tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe, which alſo, that he can powre vpon the inhabitants of the earth, when in his iuſt iudgement hee will execute the ſame, the drowning of the World in that generall deluge, and the caſting of fire and brimſtone from Heauen vpon thoſe wicked Cities of the plaine, and the rooting out of that Nation, which he did chuſe to ſerue him, doth ſufficiently teach vs. Vntill then, ſinne ſo odious to GOD, ſo grieuous vnto men, bee taken away, it is impoſſible
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17908:7"/> there ſhould be any true quietneſſe or peace vnto men. For GOD often telleth his people, howſoeuer they would flatter themſelues in their owne ſtrength or in the friendſhip of their confederates, or in their externall ceremonies and ſeruice of GOD in outward ſhew; <hi>That there is no peace to the wicked:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 48.22. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 50.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.5. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>but they ſhall lye downe in ſorrow, and feare where no feare is,</hi> becauſe they haue promiſed to themſelues, <hi>peace and ſafetie,</hi> without this atonement with God. Out of all which it doth appeare, that if wee will haue peace with God, we muſt firſt haue ſinne, this cumberſome neighbour, remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, which altogether hindereth this reconciliation, whereby we haue quietneſſe of conſciences.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Apoſtle telleth vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24.25.</note> that <hi>Wee are iuſtified freely by Gods grace, through the redemption that is in Chriſt Ieſus, whom God hath ſet forth to bee a reconciliation through faith in his bloud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation with God by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinne. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.38. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his righteouſneſſe by the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes that are paſt, through the patience of God.</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle preaching at Antioch, teacheth this Iuſtification in theſe words: <hi>Men &amp; brethren through this man is preached vnto you forgiueneſſe of ſinnes,</hi> as alſo elſewhere, <hi>By Christ we haue redemption through his bloud, the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, according to his rich grace.</hi> Which great and ineſtimable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit whoſo feeleth, hath to his vnſpeakeable comfort, a moſt ſweet taſt of that bleſſednes which the Apoſtle out of the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> mentioneth. <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiuen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. <hi>32.1, 2.</hi> Rom. <hi>4.7. S.</hi> Aug. de verb. Dom. Serm. <hi>61.</hi> Hieron. in Rom. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>or whoſe ſinnes are couered: Bleſſed is the man, to whom the Lord impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not ſinne. Fide viuenti</hi> (ſayth Saint <hi>Auguſtine) ſoluuntur pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata: He who liueth by faith, hath his ſinnes forgiuen him.</hi> And Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> hauing written thus, <hi>Per ſolam fidem iuſtificat Deus: God by faith only doth iuſtifie,</hi> doth after ſhew how this iuſtification is, and in what manner: <hi>Propoſuit per ſolam fidem peccata dimittere: He purpoſed to forgiue ſinnes by faith only.</hi> And thus by forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes, the cauſe of this dangerous iarre betweene GOD and vs being taken away, we haue boldneſſe to cal him Father, and to ſtand before him pleading not guiltie.</p>
            <p>But God gaue a Law to his people,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 23.15. Good workes.</note> 
               <hi>That none ſhould appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord emptie.</hi> So that being now freed from ſinne: yet muſt we be fraught and loden with holineſſe and righteouſneſſe. Well therefore doth Saint <hi>Peter</hi> out of the Pſalme conioyne theſe two precepts, <hi>Eſchew euill, doe good.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 34.14. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11.</note> But where ſhall this goodneſſe be had? Or how ſhall wee get any thing, that may bee acceptable to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17908:8"/> God? Our light is but darkeneſſe, our righteouſneſſe, but as ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned clothes. And when we haue indeuoured our ſelues as much as we are able to ſerue the Lord, yet ſhall we find many wants, much imperfection. It is therefore good, we doe as did <hi>Bernard,</hi> who of himſelfe thus writeth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ber. in Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. ſer.</hi> 61. Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth all our wants.</note> 
               <hi>Ego vero fidenter quod ex me mihi deest, vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po mihi ex viſceribus Domini, quia miſericordia affluunt; nec deſunt fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramina per quae effluant. I</hi> (ſayth <hi>Bernard) doe boldly take out of the bowels of the Lord that which I want of mine owne; becauſe they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with mercie, neyther want they holes by which they may guſh out.</hi> And after he addeth what holes theſe are; <hi>Foderunt manus cius, &amp; pedes eius, latuſque lancea forauerunt, &amp; per has rimas licet mihi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere mel de petra, oleumque de ſaxo duriſſimo, id eſt, guſtare &amp; videre quàm ſuauis eſt Dominus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21.16.</note> 
               <hi>They haue pierced mine hands and my feet, and haue opened my ſide with a ſpeare, and by theſe rifts, I may ſucke hony out of the rocke, and oyle out of the hardeſt ſtone, that is, I may taſte and ſee how ſweet the Lord is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we may with the greater boldneſſe claime this righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that is in Chriſt, becauſe that wee being by faith made one with Chriſt,<note place="margin">Imputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſts iuſtice.</note> and married vnto him, hee by right of marriage, is made partaker of our ſinnes, to eaſe vs of the heauie weight of that burden: and we in regard thereof too, haue an intereſt in his righteouſneſſe.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.</note> 
               <hi>For he is made vnto vs of God, wiſedome and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and ſanctification, and redemption.</hi> Which imputation of Chriſts righteouſneſſe, howſoeuer our aduerſaries doe much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.3.22 <hi>Rom.</hi> 4 5.24</note> yet <hi>Abraham</hi> had it, and it is a righteouſneſſe that belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to all that beleeue. Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> though he ſaw not all things, yet he ſaw much ſweetneſſe in this moſt comfortable doctrine, ſo much condemned in the Romiſh Church.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. Epi. <hi>90.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aſſignata eſt</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>homini aliena iustitia, qui caruit ſua; Anothers righteouſneſſe is aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to man, for that he wanted his owne.</hi> And a little after: <hi>Cur non aliunde iuſtitiae quum aliunde reatus? Why may not we haue righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from another, ſeeing guiltineſſe is from another?</hi> Againe, <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior eſt mihi donata, quam iuuata, That which is giuen mee, is ſafer then that which is bred in mee.</hi> And thus I truſt I haue ſufficiently proued, that ſinne being aboliſhed, and the condemnation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of taken away; and we appearing before God in Chriſt his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.27.</note> which is vnto vs as <hi>Eſaus</hi> garment which was vnto <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaak</hi> of a ſweet fauour; we, I ſay, ſtand as not guiltie, and haue <hi>peace with God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17908:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond difference,</hi> betweene our Aduerſaries and vs, is of the word Faith. For explanation whereof,<note place="margin">What faith is meant.</note> I will not enter into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of all the ſignifications that this word hath, but onely ſearch how in theſe wordes it muſt be taken. Our aduerſaries ſay, it is <hi>Aſſenſus ſolum firmus &amp; certus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar. de Juſtific. l. <hi>1</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ad ea omnia quae Deus credenda proponit: A conſtant and ſure aſſent only, vnto all things which God would haue vs beleeue.</hi> This is the faith that our Aduerſaries ſay, <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of, when he telleth vs, we are iuſtified by faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stapleton</hi> our Countriman, indeuoureth out of <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stap. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tid. in Rom. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.17.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ug. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ir. &amp; lit. cap. <hi>32. To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue God</hi>
               </note> to proue the ſufficiency of this definition. And to this end he allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth theſe wordes: <hi>Nulli dubtum eſt eam fidem commendari ab Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolo qua creditur Deo: No doubt the Apoſtle commendeth that faith whereby we beleeue God.</hi> Theſe wordes, wee confeſſe, are <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines,</hi> and, as he ſpeaketh them, moſt true: but by <hi>Stapleton</hi> wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted from their right and naturall ſenſe. For whereas in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapter this Father had ſpoken of two kinds of Faith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 31. To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in God.</note> the one whereby we <hi>beleeue God,</hi> the other wherby we <hi>beleeue in God:</hi> now in this Chapter he intreateth firſt of the former, commending ſuch as beleeue God, and that which hee teacheth, rather then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Maſters. And that this is <hi>Auguſtines</hi> meaning, himſelfe can beſt tell.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 32.</note> 
               <hi>We muſt inquire</hi> (ſaith this Father) <hi>what faith the Apoſtle ſo greatly commendeth, for euery beleeuing is not good. For whence is that; Brethren, beleeue not euery ſpirit, but try the ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>whether it be of God?</hi> And ſo he goeth forward, to proue that euery doctrine is not to be beleeued, and thereupon affirmeth, by way of conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that which <hi>Stapleton</hi> alleageth, that the Apoſtle commendeth the faith, whereby we beleeue that God ſaith. But after, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that <hi>S. Iames</hi> commandeth to <hi>aske in faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.6.</note> of that faith he ſaith, <hi>This is the faith whereby the iuſt man liueth; This is the faith whereby a man beleeueth in God, who iuſtifieth the wicked.</hi> And thus wee ſee how vntruly <hi>Stapleton</hi> dealeth, in the allegation of his proofe, out of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> for to iuſtifie their definition of faith.</p>
            <p>But againſt this their definition of iuſtifying faith,<note place="margin">The Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth not to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying faith only.</note> we haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers reaſons. For firſt, the rules of Logicke teach vs, that in all definitions wee muſt take heed, that the definition extend no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, then to the thing that is defined, and therefore are ſuch diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences therein to be vſed, as may diſtinguiſh that which we would define, from all other things: for otherwiſe a man ſhall not know by the definition, what a thing is, and ſo the definition ſhall not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17908:9"/> doe that, for which end only it is made. But this their definition of iuſtifying faith, extendeth further then to the thing defined. For it comprehendeth the faith which may be, and is in many wicked ones, who neither are, nor euer ſhall be iuſtified, becauſe euen they may aſſent to all the articles of Religion, as daily experience pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſufficiently.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. de verb. Dom. ſer. <hi>61.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> beſides the place before alleaged, elſewhere alſo ſpeaketh of two ſorts of faith, the one is to beleeue God, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to beleeue in God. But in his Sermons of the time, he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth three kinds of beleeuing.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Temp. ſer. <hi>181.</hi> Hebr. <hi>11.6.</hi>
               </note> Firſt, to beleeue that God is, and this is one ſtep to God, as the Apoſtle to the Hebrewes teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs: <hi>He that commeth to God, muſt beleeue that God is.</hi> The ſecond is to beleeue God, that is to ſay, that which God teacheth, and this <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> doth worthily commend (as is ſaid) but yet of it he affirmeth,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Temp. ſer. <hi>181.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>credere vera eſſe quae loquitur multi &amp; mali poſſint: Many, euen euill men, may beleeue it is true that God ſpeaketh.</hi> Now the third ſort is of ſuch as beleeue in God, which onely is that which in the Creede we confeſſe, and is auaileable to iuſtification euen by <hi>Auguſtines</hi> iudgement, as whoſo readeth his words, muſt needes acknowledge.</p>
            <p>Now our aduerſaries reſt but vpon the ſecond ſort of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and ſeeke no further. Which is much like as if a ſicke man ſhould be perſwaded, that a Phyſicion hath skill enough to helpe him, and the Apothecary hath drugs enow to doe him good, but reapeth not the fruit of the Phyſicions counſell, nor getteth any good of the Apothecaries ſtore, becauſe he neither followeth the Phyſicions counſell, nor receiueth any medicine from the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary. For ſuch a generall perſwaſion, without a particular appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, profiteth little. For this aſſent, which is in their faith, muſt not be <hi>cordis &amp; voluntatis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar. de Iuſtific. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>4</hi> &amp; <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> of the heart or will, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly teacheth vs, and others too, but only <hi>mentis &amp; intellectus: Of the minde or vnderſtanding:</hi> in ſo much as he maketh the minde or vnderſtanding, to be the ſeat of faith, noting it for a ſecond point of difference, betweene vs and them, that wee ſay faith is in the heart, which they deny, and place it only in the minde. But if in the heart it bee not, then can it not haue the application that I ſpoke of.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Faith muſt bee in the heart.</note>Againſt this their opinion, I thus reaſon: Iuſtifying faith is in the heart: Popiſh faith is not in the heart: therefore, Popiſh faith
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17908:9"/> is not that iuſtifying faith. My <hi>Minor</hi> is the doctrine of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> among other, as is ſaid before. The <hi>Maior,</hi> or firſt propoſition, <hi>S. Paul</hi> will proue for me ſufficiently, ſo that it may not be denyed.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10 10 <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>With the heart a man beleeueth vnto righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</hi> What can be more plaine? <hi>Becauſe you are ſonnes</hi> (ſaith the ſame Apoſtle elſewhere) <hi>God hath ſent forth the Spirit of his Sonne into your hearts.</hi> And what worketh it thereby? The Apoſtle tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs: <hi>Whereby wee cry Abba, Father.</hi> And how learne wee this leſſon of the Spirit? Firſt, the Spirit teacheth vs to beleeue, and to haue confidence, and then this faith bringeth forth prayer as a fruit. For, <hi>How ſhall they call on him in whom they haue not beleeued?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14</note> The Eunuch, after <hi>Philip</hi> had inſtructed him in the faith, asked, if he might not be baptized? <hi>Philip</hi> made anſwere:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.37, 38.</note> 
               <hi>If thou beleeuest with all thine heart, thou maiſt. Arator</hi> therefore, a Chriſtian Poet, who wrote about 1100. yeeres ſince, hath theſe wordes:<note place="margin">Arator in Act. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Corde ſalus credentis erit, confeſſio voce: In the heart, is the ſaluation of the beleeuer, the confeſſion is in the mouth.</hi> To be ſhort, vnfaithfulneſſe is by the Apoſtle aſſigned to the heart:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3.12</note> 
               <hi>Take heed brethren</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>leſt there be in any of you at any time an euill heart and vnfaithfull, to depart away from the liuing God;</hi> therefore, by the Law of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries, faith muſt be in the heart too.</p>
            <p>A third fault, that I find, with this definition, is, that they ſay, it is <hi>aſſenſus ſolùm: An aſſent onely,</hi>
               <note place="margin">No true faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. <hi>Bellar. de Iuſtific. l.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note> as before out of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> I ſhewed; whereby their meaning is to exclude knowledge, as a thing nothing at all required in faith. In ſo much as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſhameth not to affirme, that <hi>fides melius per ignorantiam quàm per notitiam definitur: Faith is better defined by ignorance, then by know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> But herein the common prouerbe is verified, <hi>plus vident o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi quàm oculus: Mo eyes ſee more then one.</hi> For the Vniuerſity of Colen, in their Cenſure,<note place="margin">Cenſur. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. explic. Dial. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> written againſt <hi>Monhemius</hi> (though they were Papiſts, and in other points aduerſaries to the truth) yet in this write farre otherwiſe then <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth: <hi>Fidei ratio in fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma notitia conſiſtit: The definition</hi> (ſay they) <hi>of faith, ſtandeth vpon firme knowledge.</hi> We cannot herein ſpeake more contrary to <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> then they haue done.</p>
            <p>Yet, true it is, that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in the Booke and Chapter, laſt alleaged by mee, granteth, that in faith there is a kinde of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; for, <hi>he ſaith there are in him, that beleeueth, two things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar. de Iuſtif. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>aſſent and apprehenſion,</hi> which apprehenſion, he ſaith, is <hi>notitia rudis &amp;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17908:10"/> confuſa: A rude and confuſed knowledge.</hi> A knowledge, belike, ſuch as his ſight was,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 8.24.</note> who <hi>ſaw men walking like trees,</hi> ſauing, that this knowledge is not like to bring forth ſo good an effect, as his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfit ſight did.<note place="margin">25.</note> For, he ſoone after <hi>was reſtored to his ſight, and ſaw euery man a farre off cleerely:</hi> but they who ſeeke for faith in this confuſed knowledge, ſhall neuer finde it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing knowledge the Papiſts brag of.</note>And if you deſire to know what this confuſed knowledge is, wherewith they content themſelues; you may giue a great gheſſe thereof, by that which they tell vs of the Colliars faith, holden for a true faith in the Romiſh Church, commended by <hi>Staphilus</hi> that ſlanderous Apoſtata, approued alſo by <hi>Stapleton,</hi> who tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that idle pamphlet.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Staphilus</hi> his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie.</note> The Colliar told the Deuill, he beleeued as the Church beleeueth, and the Church beleeued as he did. But further, what the Church beleeued or himſelfe either, he could not tell. This is that confuſed knowledge then, that they would, men ſhould content themſelues withall; to bee able to ſpeake of the Church in generall, but not of the particular doctrine thereof, to call God Father, but not to know by what meanes hee is our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: to ſay, wee beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt, not vnderſtanding any thing of his perſon, or office. And thus, not to know how to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply vnto our ſelues, the comfort of theſe, or any other generall points, is a found faith with our great Maſters of Rome. But though <hi>Staphilus</hi> ſay, the <hi>Deuill was ouercome with that anſwere, and put to flight:</hi> yet, ſure I am, that God requireth greater knowledge, and therefore giueth his word, and appointeth his miniſterie for the inſtruction of his people.<note place="margin">A particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is needfull. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.26.</note> Neither did <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuppoſe ſuch a generall knowledge would ſerue the turne, when hee ſo ſtraitly chargeth the Iſraelites, to inſtruct their children in the true cauſe of their feaſt of Paſſeouer. <hi>When your children</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>aske you what ſeruice is this you keepe; Then ſhall yee ſay, It is the ſacrifice of the Lords Paſſeouer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">27.</note> 
               <hi>which paſſed ouer the houſes of the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael in Aegypt, when he ſmote the Aegyptians, &amp; preſerued our houſes. Ioſhua</hi> alſo thought it not enough, that Gods people ſhould haue a generall perſwaſion, that God was good, but hee tooke order, that his particular benefits ſhould bee remembred euen of their children.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 4.6, 7.</note> And when <hi>Ioſhua</hi> would that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould forbid <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad</hi> and <hi>Medad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 11.29</note> to prophecie in the Hoſt, <hi>Moſes</hi> anſwered, <hi>Would God that all the Lords people were Prophets, and the Lord would put his Spirit vpon them,</hi> wiſhing a more ſpeciall knowledge vnto them,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17908:10"/> then was ordinary among Gods people. And the Apoſtle prayeth, that the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> may be <hi>fulfilled with knowledge of Gods will in all wiſedome and ſpirituall vnderſtanding.</hi> He addeth his reaſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.9.</note> that <hi>you may walke worthy of the Lord, and pleaſe him in all things:</hi>
               <note place="margin">10.</note> giuing vs thereby to vnderſtand, that without particular knowledge of his will, in all things we cannot pleaſe him. But, what ſtand I vpon this point? Doth not Saint <hi>Peter</hi> (who they ſay was the firſt Pope, and therefore that he commandeth, they will confeſſe muſt bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed) require ſuch knowledge in euery Chriſtian,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.</note> that <hi>they may be readie to giue anſwere to euery man, that asketh a reaſon of the hope that is in them?</hi> Shall wee then content our ſelues againſt ſo many expreſſe teſtimonies of the word, with that rude and confuſed knowledge of <hi>Bellarmines,</hi> or the Colliars faith, ſo well liked of <hi>Staphilus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what reaſon haue they ſo to reioyce in this dimme light,<note place="margin">Why this generall knowlege is ſo prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3 20.</note> like ſuch as haue ſore eies, and therefore hang ſomething before them, to keepe the brightneſſe of the light from them? Our Sauiour Chriſt yeeldeth the reaſon in theſe words, <hi>Euery man that doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, hateth the light, neither commeth to the light, leſt his deedes ſhould be reprooued.</hi> Our aduerſaries teach ſo many doctrines which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide the light of the word, and touchſtone of truth: they haue deuiſed, and daily doe deuiſe, ſo many fruitleſſe workes, and blind deuotions, ſo many falſe and wil-worſhippings, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious ſeruices, repugnant to the Sacred Scriptures, and ſo little ſauouring of that obedience, that is, eyther commended in the godly, or commaunded in the word: that to cloke the wickedneſſe and abomination in many, but folly and vanitie in the beſt of theſe their deuices, they are forced to tell the people, that ignorance is the mother of Deuotion (for ſo they may lead them into a very dungeon of Superſtition) and that a folded vp faith, is good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for them;<note place="margin">Stapl. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dot. in Act. <hi>16.31.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nec aliam ſimplex &amp; idiota Chriſtianus habere te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur; neither is a ſimple and vnlearned Chriſtian bound to haue any other faith.</hi> Is not this the way to make fooles and idiots of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? This, this, I ſay, is the way to caſt men into a gulfe of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.15.</note> and to make men <hi>two-fold more the children of hell then you are.</hi> And then with, an <hi>Iöpoean,</hi> you reioyce, that Ignorance hath hatched many Deuotions. A mother worthie of ſuch badde Daughters.</p>
            <p>Now, this aſſent being proued to bee no true iuſtifying faith
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17908:11"/> (for thereby wee only beleeue that which God teacheth, not in God, as in our Creed we profeſſe) let vs ſtep a little forward, and ſee what this faith is, which we affirme doth iuſtifie. And if wee rightly conſider thereof,<note place="margin">True faith.</note> we ſhall find <hi>two things</hi> neceſſarie for one that beleeueth; the one is <hi>Knowledge,</hi> the other is the <hi>Application</hi> of that our knowledge.<note place="margin">Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note> 
               <hi>That knowledge is neceſſarie to attaine to faith,</hi> if we had no other proofe, yet this were ſufficient, that God vſeth ſo many wayes for the inſtruction of his people, that by Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance they ſhould not erre. Hee giueth his Law to bee a rule of life and Religion, appointeth his Prieſts to teach the ſame, and to ſupply their negligence, hee ſendeth his Prophets, extraordinary Meſſengers, to iogge his people vpon the elbow, ſo putting them in minde when they did amiſſe. And hath hee not ordained the Miniſterie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.13 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26.</note> that wee may <hi>meete together in the vnitie of faith and knowledge of the Sonne of God?</hi> The ſundry gifts that GOD hath giuen vnto his Church, ought all to bee imployed to the edifying thereof.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> office was, <hi>to make readie a people prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the Lord,</hi> as the Angell doth foreſhew, or as <hi>Zacharie</hi> his father ſayth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.76.</note> 
               <hi>To prepare the way of the Lord, that is, to make men fit to beleeue in Chriſt.</hi> And how doth he execute this his function? <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by giuing knowledge of ſaluation vnto Gods people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">77.</note> 
               <hi>by the remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ſinnes.</hi> Our Sauiour Chriſt thus ſpeaketh vnto the Iewes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.38.</note> 
               <hi>If I doe</hi> (the workes of my Father) <hi>then though you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue not mee, beleeue the workes, that ye may know and beleeue.</hi> As if he would ſay, Vnleſſe you know, you cannot beleeue; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider of my workes, that you may know, and ſo beleeue. To this purpoſe alſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 15.7.</note> is that which Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid: <hi>Among vs</hi> (the Apoſtles) <hi>God choſe out me, that the Gentiles by my mouth ſhould heare the word of the Goſpell and beleeue.</hi> Now, it is moſt plaine, that men heare (vnleſſe they bee ſuch forgetfull hearers as S. <hi>Iames</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liketh) that they may know,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.24.</note> and ſo beleeue. But that I may bee ſhort, <hi>Knowledge</hi> is ſo neceſſarie for ſuch as beleeue, as that <hi>it is taken for faith it ſelfe,</hi> and that by one that did know better how to ſpeake of theſe matters,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.3.</note> then all our Romiſh Rabbies. <hi>This is life eternall</hi> (ſayth Chriſt) <hi>to know thee to bee the only very God,</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that it is life eternall to beleeue God, to bee the only verie God, and whom hee had ſent, Ieſus Chriſt: and ſuch ſpeeches are common in the Scripture.</p>
            <p>But as meate how good ſo euer nouriſheth not, but ſuch as eate
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17908:11"/> it: and Phyſicke, be it neuer ſo medicinable, helpeth not but ſuch as receiue it: Euen ſo,<note place="margin">Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſecond thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in faith.</note> 
               <hi>if this knowledge be not applyed to the grieued or wounded conſcience, the offendour ſhall neuer haue peace with God therby.</hi> The Apoſtle hauing handled at the ful the example of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and ſet forth his conſtant faith, with the comfortable effect it had, <hi>That it was imputed to him for righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.22.23.24.</note> then teacheth vs by application what vſe we muſt make thereof: <hi>It was not written for him only, that it was imputed to him for righteouſneſſe; but alſo for vs to whom it ſhall be imputed, which beleeue in him, who rayſed vp Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Lord from the dead.</hi> Notably for this point,<note place="margin">Benard. de Annunt. Serm. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> writeth. <hi>Si credas peccata tua non poſſe deleri, niſi ab illo cui ſoli pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſti, &amp; in quem peccata non cadunt, bene facis: If thou beleeue thy ſinnes cannot be done away, but by him againſt whom thou haſt only ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and who himſelfe is not ſubiect to ſinne, thou doſt well.</hi> Here is a good and a Chriſtian knowledge: now marke what vſe wee muſt make of it. <hi>Sed adde adhuc</hi> (ſayth he in that verie place) <hi>vt &amp; hoc credas, quia per ipſum peccata tibi donantur. Hoc eſt teſtimonium quod perhibet Spiritus Sanctus in corde tuo, Dimiſſa ſunt tibi peccata tua: But yet adde this</hi> (ſayth good <hi>Bernard) that thou alſo beleeue, that by him thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee. This is the teſtimonie that the holy Ghost beareth in thine heart, Thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee.</hi> Heere wee haue a particular application of that generall knowledge before mentioned.</p>
            <p>And out of this place of <hi>Bernard,</hi> wee are by the way to note, how the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church which would (though moſt vniuſtly) bee counted the true Church, hath this long time deceiued the world, in making men beleeue, the Pope hath power to forgiue ſinnes;<note place="margin">Man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue ſins.</note> whereas Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> moſt plainly, and to the Scriptures moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeably doth teach, that God only can forgiue ſinnes, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our ſinne is a breach of his Law, and himſelfe cannot ſinne. Fye, therefore vpon that man of ſinne, who being himſelfe full fraught with ſinne, and ouerloden with wickedneſſe, dare take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him that office, that belongeth only to our Sinne-leſſe GOD. <hi>He only can make cleane that which is conceiued of vncleane ſeed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 14.4.</note> and beſides him none. He, I ſay, hee only, can truly make this Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>I, I am he that putteth away thine iniquities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 43.25.</note> 
               <hi>for mine owne ſake, and will not remember thy ſinnes.</hi> Howſoeuer that graceleſſe wretch, <hi>Boniface</hi> the eighth, who inſtituted the firſt Romiſh Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, giuing therein immunitie both from ſinne, and the puniſhment
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17908:12"/> thereof, would make the world beleeue that hee hath power to forgiue ſinnes too.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anton. part.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 8 <hi>tit.</hi> 20. §. 2. The fruit of appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. <hi>Praefat. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort. ad Martyr. ad Fortuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Job.</hi> 19.25.26. <hi>Micah.</hi> 7.7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15</note> But as <hi>Antoninus</hi> Biſhop of Florence, writing that Hiſtorie, ſayth, <hi>God only forgiueth ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to returne, from whence for a few lines I haue digreſſed. When we can in this ſort apply vnto our ſelues the mercy of God, and thus make a garment fitting our ſelues, to couer therewith our ſhame of <hi>the wooll of the Lambe</hi> (as <hi>Cyprian</hi> in one place prettily ſpeaketh) (for ſo he calleth the Scripture.) Oh, with what aſſurance will wee bee able with <hi>Iob</hi> to ſay, <hi>I am ſure my Redeemer liueth, I ſhall ſee God in my fleſh.</hi> And with <hi>Micah: I will waite for God my Sauiour, my God will heare me.</hi> And with the Apoſtle, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus came into the World to ſaue ſinners, whereof I am chiefe. Notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for this cauſe was I receiued to mercie, that Ieſus Chriſt ſhould firſt ſhew on me all long ſuffering, vnto the example of them, who ſhall, in time to come, beleeue in hir <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eternall life.</hi> But the Apoſtle ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in many places vnſpeakeable comfort, by applying to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in particular, the mercies of God, in ſo much as hee aſſureth himſelfe, that none could charge Gods ſeruants to indanger them, none could condemne them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33.35.38.39.</note> 
               <hi>Yea, who ſhall ſeparate vs</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>from the loue of Chriſt? I am perſwaded, that neither death, nor life, nor the Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, is able to ſeparate vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</hi> Thus wee ſee what wonderfull aſſurance and confidence they haue, whom Gods Spirit guideth, to apply vnto their wounded conſciences, the moſt Soueraigne ſalue of the promiſes and examples of Gods mercie. Whereas others in the time of feare and danger, languiſh in perplexitie,<note place="margin">Luk. <hi>23 30.</hi> Bernard. de Annunt. ſerm <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and could wiſh <hi>the mountaines would fall vpon them, and the hills would couer them.</hi> For truly (ſayth <hi>Bernard</hi>) as it were ſpeaking vnto God, <hi>Non reponis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leum miſericordiae, niſi in vaſe fidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae: Thou, Lord, putteſt not the oyle of mercie, but into the veſſell of confidence.</hi> This, this, I ſay, is the faith commended by the Apoſtle, this is the faith that iuſtifieth before God, which beginning with knowledge of Gods mercy in Chriſt Ieſus, out of it gathereth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and boldnes.</p>
            <p>And thus with good warrant out of the Word, I truſt wee may affirme, that this faith which doth aſſuredly know, and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly apply vnto vs the promiſed mercies of God, cauſeth vs with boldneſſe to ſtand before God without feare of condemnation:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17908:12"/> yet not for the merit or worthineſſe of the act of beleeuing; but becauſe the office, yea the very nature of faith is, to apprehend and take hold of Chriſt, through whom wee are found righteous before God: in that he is made vnto vs of God, <hi>wiſedome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30</note> 
               <hi>and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and ſanctification, and redemption,</hi> as before I haue ſaid.</p>
            <p>The laſt wordes in this ſentence,<note place="margin">What workes of the Law are meant.</note> whereof there is any queſtion betweene our aduerſaries and vs, are theſe, <hi>The workes of the Law.</hi> Out of theſe ariſe <hi>two doubts.</hi> The firſt is, what Law the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of in theſe wordes. For ſome, euen very ancient, haue beene in that error, that he ſpeaketh of the Law ceremoniall, as <hi>Origen,</hi> and others. Now the Romiſh Church, not ſeeing how they might maintayne their doctrine of Merits, and Iuſtification by workes, vnleſſe they were of that minde alſo; were in former times of that mind too, being glad that they might ſhrowd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnder the name of ancient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rs. I need not ſpeake in particular of theſe Popiſh Writers, ſeeing <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confeſſeth as much as I ſay. <hi>Nonnulli</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>è Catholicis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar. de Iuſtific. l <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>docent per opera quae Apoſtolus à iuſtificatione excludit, intelligi obſeruationem lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium ceremoniarum: Many of the Catholikes teach, that by the workes which the Apoſtle excludeth from iuſtification, the obſeruation of the ceremoniall Law is meant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how many, or how great in learning,<note place="margin">Not works ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.13.</note> or accompt ſoeuer they be: <hi>S. Paul</hi> affordeth vs proofe enough to conuince them of error. When he ſaith, <hi>The doers of the Law ſhall be iuſtified,</hi> is there any colour of reaſon to imagine, that they who obſerue the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Law, ſhall bee iuſtified? Wee ſee in the firſt and laſt Chapters of the Prophet <hi>Eſay, Micah</hi> the 6. the 50. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> and in other places of Scripture, that many, who were moſt diligent performers of the ceremonies, were notwithſtanding miſliked of God, yea reproued for ſatisfying themſelues with that externall ſeruice. <hi>What haue I to doe with the multitude of your ſacrifices,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>ſaith the Lord, I am full of the burnt offrings of Rams, and of the fat of fed beaſts, and I deſire not the bloud of Bullocks, nor of Lambs, nor of Goates.</hi> That alſo, which the Apoſtle writeth <hi>of the effect of the Law, written in mens hearts,</hi> by reaſon whereof, <hi>we haue thoughts accuſing &amp; excuſing,</hi> cannot be vnderſtood of the Law ceremonial.</p>
            <p>But to come yet neerer to the purpoſe, <hi>S. Paul,</hi> euen in that place where hee handleth this queſtion, concluding the former part of this diſcourſe, and hauing proued Iewes and Gentiles to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17908:13"/> of the Law, either written or of nature, thus ſaith, <hi>Therefore by the workes of the Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall no fleſh be iuſtified in Gods ſight.</hi> And leſt we might make any doubt what Law hee meaneth of, he yeeldeth a reaſon of his former aſſertion, which maketh the matter plaine. <hi>For by the Law is knowledge of ſinne.</hi> And yet that it may be more manifeſt what Law is here meant, elſwhere in plaine wordes he expoundeth himſelfe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom</hi> 7.7.</note> 
               <hi>I knew not ſinne, but by the Law: For I had not known lust, except the Law had ſaid, Thou ſhalt not lust.</hi> Out of which wordes I reaſon thus: The Apoſtle ſpeaketh of that Law, that maketh vs to know ſinne; but that is not the Law ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall: therefore the Apoſtle ſpeaketh not of the Law cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall.</p>
            <p>Yea, this place ſeemed to <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> to haue ſuch force, as that thereupon he groundeth that which we teach.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Spir. &amp; lit. cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ac ne quiſquam pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taret hic Apoſtolum ea lege dixiſſe hominem iuſtificari, quae in Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis veteribus multa continet figurata praecepta, &amp;c. And leſt any man ſhould thinke the Apoſtle to haue ſaid, that a man is iuſtified by that, which in the old Sacraments haue many figuratiue precepts, from whence commeth circumciſion, which children were commended to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue: he by and by ſheweth what Law he meant, and ſaith, For by the Law is knowledge of ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Apoſtle himſelfe is beſt Interpreter of his owne mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Out of that he had ſaid, ſome perchance would gather, that he had little regard to the Law, whereby the Iewes would be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, (for they knew the Law was giuen of God.) Others would take occaſion thereupon more boldly to tranſgreſſe: to meet therefore with theſe inconueniences, hee maketh vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe this obiection:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31.</note> 
               <hi>Doe wee then make the Law of no effect through faith? Yea, we eſtabliſh the Law.</hi> But the Law ceremoniall is not by the Goſpell eſtabliſhed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4.</note> but aboliſhed. <hi>For that Law had but the ſhaddow of good things to come. But the end of the Law is Chriſt.</hi> So that he, offering himſelfe vpon the Altar of the Croſſe to God the Father,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.30:</note> a ſacrifice for ſin, did vpon good ground ſay, <hi>It is finiſhed.</hi> So as Chriſt being come, if wee will ſtill tye our ſelues to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of that Law,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> telleth vs, that <hi>Chriſt ſhall profit vs nothing.</hi>
               <note place="margin">4.</note> 
               <hi>Yee are</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>aboliſhed from Chriſt, whoſoeuer are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Law, yee are fallen from grace.</hi> Therefore were the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in their dayes very carefull, to teach men to reſt vpon Chriſt, and not to imagine that now in the time of the Goſpell, they are
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17908:13"/> tyed to <hi>thoſe impotent and beggerly rudiments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.9.</note> as the Apoſtle calleth them. This may appeare by that notable Councell, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. and in diuers places. Much more might bee alleaged, to proue that the Law ceremoniall cannot in this place be vnderſtood. But this, I truſt, is ſufficient: and had indeed beene more then enough, but that our Aduerſaries of later time,<note place="margin">Bellar. de Iuſtif. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi> Andrad. Orthodox. Explic. l <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> although they dare not defend that opinion, yet would they make it ſeeme leſſe abſurd, as doth <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> in pointing to ſome places that their errour is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon, as if they had reaſon ſo to teach, and <hi>Andradius</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſome Fathers of that minde.</p>
            <p>Well then, by the Law, without all queſtion wee muſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Law morall. But here ariſeth <hi>another doubt,</hi> what works are here excluded in theſe wordes,<note place="margin">What workes are exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> 
               <hi>Without the workes of the Law.</hi> And here our aduerſaries doe earneſtly contend, not to haue all workes excluded from Iuſtification, but ſuch only as are done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they beleeued. For if they ſhould confeſſe that no works can iuſtifie, then falleth downe that doctrine of Merits to the ground; a moſt gainefull doctrine to Pope and Popiſh Prieſts (who muſt ſupply with their ſtore, that which other want of their owne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.) But we teach that all workes,<note place="margin">All works before &amp; after, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification.</note> aſwell ſuch as follow our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification (this our aduerſaries denie) as the workes that wee doe afore our iuſtification (which themſelues confeſſe) are in theſe wordes excluded, from being any cauſes of our iuſtification be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</p>
            <p>And to auerre this, which we ſay, we haue many ſtrong reaſons. The firſt is taken from the wordes themſelues, being mightily ſtrengthned with the faithfulneſſe of him who teacheth this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and with his ſincerity in teaching. For as hee requireth in other <hi>diſpoſers of the ſecrets of God, that euery man be found faithfull:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2.</note> ſo he teſtifieth of his owne faithfulneſſe in his miniſtery, ſpeaking vnto the Elders of the Church of Epheſus.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20.20.</note> 
               <hi>I kept backe nothing</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that was profitable, but haue ſhewed you, and taught you o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly, and throughout euery houſe.</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">27.</note> 
               <hi>I haue kept nothing backe, but haue ſhewed you all the counſell of God.</hi> Neither can wee in reaſon ſuppoſe he would deale more ſincerely with them of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus, then with the Romanes, of whoſe inſtruction in the faith how carefull hee was, may well bee ſeene in his firſt and fifteenth Chapters of that Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle therefore,<note place="margin">All with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</note> ſpeaking of workes without any excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17908:14"/> as hee doth <hi>(without the workes of the Law)</hi> if any workes ſhould not haue beene excluded from iuſtification, he might haue beene charged by the Romanes, that he kept backe ſomwhat from them, namely, what workes were to be admitted as cauſes of iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and what not: and ſo did not ſhew them all the counſell of God. For if he had beene of our aduerſaries opinion, ſincerity would haue forced him to haue ſaid, When I ſay, we are iuſtified without workes, I ſpeake only of workes done afore we are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, not of all workes. For when we are once iuſtified by God, then by our workes wee muſt iuſtifie our ſelues. So that if any workes may be accounted as cauſes of our iuſtification, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles manner of ſpeaking would rather haue beſeemed ſome acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocating Prieſt or Ieſuite, who haue taught their hearts to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble, and their tongues to lye, yea who profeſſe to teach the arte of diſſimulation, and cogging, and glory in their falſhood, whereby they deceiue the world, then this faithfull Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>It is moſt certayne therefore, that the Apoſtle, being as he was, a moſt faithfull diſpoſer of the myſteries of God, one that dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted all ſuch doubtfull or double dealing in Gods matters eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſe preaching ſtandeth not in the iniycing ſpeech of mans wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but in the plaine euidence of Spirit and power,</hi> excepting no workes, excludeth all. And many ſuch like ſpeeches we haue in Scriptures, in which ſuch indefinite propoſitions (as Logicians call them) are vniuerſally to bee vnderſtood.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4.15.</note> Chriſt is ſaid to <hi>bee without ſinne.</hi> Now, ſeeing there is ſinne Originall and Actuall, of commiſſion, and of omiſſion, ſhall we imagine, that becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith not without <hi>(all)</hi> ſinne, therefore Chriſt is ſubiect to ſome ſinne?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.4.</note> God maketh promiſe to his people, that <hi>Ieruſalem ſhall be inhabited without wall.</hi> Now, becauſe there are ſundry ſorts of walls, ſome of ſtone, ſome of earth, or of other matter, as men fancy: ſhall ſome cauilling companion ſay, Though they had no ſtone walls, yet had they ſome other walls for their ſtrength? But infinite ſuch places might bee brought, wherein it may eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that though this vniuerſall ſigne <hi>(all)</hi> be not added, yet it muſt be vnderſtood, as alſo it muſt be in theſe wordes of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> as well all workes going before, or following iuſtification, as all Lawes, either Naturall, or Morall, or Ceremoniall.</p>
            <p>Againe, if the Apoſtle had meant only to exclude the workes done in our infidelity, he needed not ſo carefully to haue ſet down
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17908:14"/> the manner of our Iuſtification, as he doth immediatly before theſe words: That it is <hi>by the righteouſneſſe of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22.24.</note> 
               <hi>by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, vnto all, and vpon all that beleeue.</hi> And that, <hi>Wee are iuſtified freely by his grace, through the Redemption that is in Chriſt Ieſus, whom God hath ſet forth to bee a reconciliation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">25.</note> 
               <hi>through faith in his bloud, to declare his righteouſneſſe, by the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes.</hi> In all which, there is not one word of Workes, but all is aſcribed to Chriſt. Wherein the Apoſtle, alſo writeth ſo carefully, and ſo wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, as if he feared nothing more, then, that man ſhould reſt any thing vpon his Merits. To conclude therefore this my firſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>If it be of grace, it is no more of Workes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.6</note> 
               <hi>or elſe were grace, no more grace: but if it bee of Workes, it is no more grace; for then were Workes no more Workes.</hi> So that, becauſe the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſayth, it is of grace, and by faith without Workes, therefore Workes are wholly excluded, as <hi>Andradius</hi> himſelfe will warrant me to ſay. For, <hi>Mercedis ratio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Andrad. Orthodox. Explicat. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>cum gratiae nomine ex aduerſo pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. For the conſideration of reward</hi> (or Merit) <hi>is cleane contrarie to grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond argument I take from the finall cauſes of this doctrine of Iuſtification by faith only, which are two, ſet downe by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. The one in this Chapter, immediately before the words of my Text; namely, to exclude our reioycing or boaſting. But if all workes bee not diſabled, as inſufficient cauſes of our Iuſtification, ſome workes ſhould be left, wherein we might reioyce.<note place="margin">To ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing in our ſelues.</note> For by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing, the Apoſtle meaneth nothing elſe, but that confidence that men haue, whereby they content themſelues, as if they were out of danger of Gods wrath. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> then concluding out of that he hath taught of Iuſtification by faith, that our reioycing is thereby taken away, teacheth vs thus much, that whoſo apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with an aſſured faith this Iuſtification, that we haue by Chriſt, reſteth nothing vpon his owne workes, or contenteth not himſelfe with the righteouſneſſe that is by the Law. But on the contrarie, our Aduerſaries ſuppoſe their reioycing is not taken away. In ſo much, as a great man among them dareth affirme,<note place="margin">Andrad. Orthodox. Explicat. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That heauenly bliſſe is not ſo freely giuen of God, and liberally, as in reſpect of their workes it is due.</hi> And by and by after: <hi>We gather, that eternall felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ought not to bee imputed according to grace, but according to debt.</hi> And therefore within a few words after, he alſo defineth Merit,<note place="margin">Merit.</note> 
               <hi>A free action whereunto a reward is due.</hi> Which Doctrine of <hi>Andra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:17908:15"/> becauſe it is alſo the Doctrine of the Romiſh Church, wee may truly affirme of them, that they doe, what in them lyeth, to make the Apoſtle a Lyer, when hee affirmeth that reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing is taken away by the Law of faith: ſeeing they ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce and content themſelues in their workes. But I will end this with one ſhort argument: If Iuſtification may bee by workes, then is not our reioycing in the Law taken away by faith: but it is by faith taken away: therefore Iuſtification is not by workes. The <hi>Minor</hi> propoſition is the wordes of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.6.</note> The <hi>Maior</hi> is proued by that, which a little before out of the Apoſtle I alleadged, that workes and grace cannot both ſtand as cauſes of our Iuſtification. But notably for this purpoſe, doth <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> gather out of theſe words:<note place="margin">Chryſ. in Epiſt. ad Rom. hom. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>If the faithfull man, and he who is ſaued, would thinke well of himſelfe in this reſpect that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth the Law, doe heare in theſe words, how by the Law it ſelfe his mouth is ſtopped, how by the Law hee is accuſed, how the Law it ſelfe denieth as it were ſaluation to ſinners, and excludeth all boaſting: and he who as yet beleeueth not, being hereby deiected and humbled, may take occaſion to draw neere vnto faith: thou ſeeſt how great force faith hath, how it driueth vs from whatſoeuer we had before, not ſuffering vs to reioyce though neuer ſo little, in them.</hi> And a little before he hath ſayd that God ſaueth, <hi>Nullis ad hoc vſus operibus, ſed fidem tantum exigens: Not vſing</hi> (for our Iuſtification) <hi>any workes, but requiring faith only.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sedul. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad Rom. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sedulius</hi> alſo verie well noteth thus, <hi>Talis gloriatio quae veniebat ex operibus legis excluditur. Such reioycing is excluded as commeth of the workes of the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</note>Another end why our Iuſtification is by faith, is for our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable comfort, <hi>That it might come by grace, and the promiſe might bee ſure to all the ſeed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16.</note> Whereas if wee ſhould ſeeke to get the inheritance by the Law,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.18.</note> we could not thinke to haue it by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and ſo in reſpect of our owne manifold imperfections, wee might alwayes bee doubtfull and wauering, and farre from that comfort, that Gods children finde in themſelues. In this reſpect then, it is good, that we perſwade our ſelues, that we are ſaued by grace,<note place="margin">Bell. de Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtific. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> that we may looke vnto Chriſt only. Yea, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe giueth this aduice: <hi>Propter incertitudinem propriae iuſtitiae, &amp; periculum inanis gloriae, tutiſſimum eſt fiduciam totam in ſola Dei mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordia ponere. In reſpect of the vncertaintie of our owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the danger of vaine glorie, the ſafeſt way, is to put all our
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17908:15"/> confidence, only in Gods mercy and goodneſſe.</hi> Very well writeth vpon theſe words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Theophilact:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theophil. in Epiſt. ad Rom. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quum vniuerſa ſint in Dei, tum gratia, tum miſericordia, fita, profecto quae ab eoconfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runtur, ſtabilia fore &amp; certa omni ſemini, id eſt, credentibus cunctis exiſtimanda ſunt. Seeing all things are of Gods grace and mercie: ſure the things that are giuen from him, as it may be thought, are ſtable and ſure to all the ſeed, that is, to all beleeuers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. in Epiſt. ad Rom. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> alſo ſayth, <hi>Firma eſſe non potest, promiſſio omni ſemini, hoc eſt omni homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ex omni gente, niſi fuerit ex fide: The promiſe cannot bee firme vnto all the ſeed, that is, to all men of euery Nation, vnleſſe it bee of faith.</hi> And he after yeeldeth a reaſon of that he hath ſaid, becauſe by the Law we are found guiltie, and the promiſe cannot be giuen to them that are guiltie, vnleſſe they bee purified, which muſt bee done by faith. Thus then I reaſon, The promiſe of Iuſtification muſt be ſure: but vnleſſe it be of faith, it cannot be ſure: therefore the promiſe of Iuſtification muſt bee of faith. The <hi>Maior</hi> is Saint <hi>Pauls, Rom.</hi> 4.16. The <hi>Minor</hi> is the former wordes of Saint <hi>Ambroſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A third argument to proue, that euen the workes of them that are regenerate, cannot iuſtifie, and are excluded by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> from hauing that force, is taken from the example of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who is ſet forth as a patterne, in whom wee may learne how wee all can attaine to Iuſtification, as it is plaine to ſee in the fourth Chapter of this Epiſtle to the Romanes. <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> not iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by workes.</note> a good while after he was called out of Vr of the Chaldees, had liued a good time in obedience vnto GOD, had done no doubt, many good Workes, and offered many Sacrifices vnto God: yet, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect vnto any of his Workes, that hee now the childe and ſeruant of God had done: <hi>Abraham beleeued God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 15 6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.9.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>and that</hi> (his beleeuing) <hi>was imputed to him for righteouſneſſe.</hi> And therefore, <hi>Paul</hi> is bolde to vſe ſuch excluſiue words: <hi>The promiſe was not giuen through the Law, but through the righteouſneſſe of faith.</hi> And, <hi>Sicut</hi> Abrahae, <hi>&amp; noſtra filiorum eius per gratiam,</hi> ſayth <hi>Primaſius:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Primaſ. in Epiſt. ad Rom. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>As was</hi> (the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification) <hi>of</hi> Abrahams, <hi>ſo is ours alſo, who are his children, by grace.</hi> But to be ſhort, I ſuppoſe, we may bee bold to gather out of that which is ſaid, this reaſon. As <hi>Abraham</hi> was iuſtified, ſo ſhall wee bee: but <hi>Abraham</hi> was iuſtified by faith, without the workes that he did, being Gods ſeruant, therefore we alſo ſhall ſo be iuſtified. All this argument may well and ſtrongly be prooued
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17908:16"/> out of this fourth Chapter of the Epiſtle to the Romanes.</p>
            <p>But what neede many Arguments? <hi>Confitentem habemus reum. Stapleton</hi> our Countriman, a ſure friend to the Romiſh Church, and as loth as any of them, to write any thing that might any way im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne their Popiſh <hi>Maximes,</hi> ſeeing the deadly wound which theſe words of the Apoſtle giue to their Doctrine of Merits, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry carefull to ſalue that ſore: yet the force of truth driueth him to grant that heere the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antidot. in Rom.</hi> 3.28. Our works cannot merit for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes.</note> 
               <hi>Excludit opera à virtute iuſtificandi ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutè, id eſt, à virtute remittendi peccata: Excludeth Workes from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing power ſimply or abſolutely to iuſtifie, that is, to remit ſinne, or from power to remit ſin.</hi> What can be more plaine? Good Workes cannot obtaine remiſſion of ſins, ſayth <hi>Stapleton,</hi> and therefore not iuſtifie abſolutely or perfitly. Now, an vnperfit Iuſtification we are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted withal, neither hath Chriſt or any of his Apoſtles taught vs any ſuch. But we know that a perfect cauſe hath her perfect ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, a perfit Sacrifice (ſuch an one was that which Chriſt offered) hath obtained perfect Iuſtification before God for all beleeuers.</p>
            <p>But heere, I would faine haue asked a queſtion of <hi>Stapleton,</hi> if he had beene aliue, or of ſome other friend of his, (ſeeing hee is gone, to giue an account, how well he hath vſed his talent, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to gaine ſoules to Chriſt or to Antichriſts) how Pariſh Prieſts ſhall doe hereafter? When men and women come to bee ſhriuen, and haue confeſſed their ſinnes, ſhall their Ghoſtly Father, bid them faſt ſo many Frydayes, Wedneſdayes, or Saints Eeues, gad on Pilgrimage to Hales or Buxton, to Compoſtel, to Rome, or to Loretta, weare Haire-cloth next their skinne, goe bare-foote and bare-legged? ſhall they torment their bodie with Whips, or other puniſhments,<note place="margin">Popiſh pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances plaine co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zenages.</note> or begger their Poſteritie in building Chaunteries, and ſuch like places, for ſatisfaction for ſinne? All this is to no purpoſe. For <hi>Stapleton</hi> aſſureth vs, there is in theſe, or any other, though better workes by farre, ſuch as GOD hath commanded, no power to remit ſinne; ſo that Iuſtification muſt bee ſought for ſome better way. And ſo it ſeemeth, the World hath beene cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zened a great while by theſe cogging Companions, which haue made men and women beleeue, that by ſuch Workes they may ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie for their ſinnes. And thus I truſt vpon ſo good a confeſſion of <hi>Stapleton,</hi> ſo good warrant of the Word, and ſure grounds of doctrine, wee may conclude that a man is iuſtified and accounted guiltleſſe before God, by faith apprehending Chriſt Ieſus, in whom
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17908:16"/> we haue redemption by forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes, without any Merit of our Wrokes, whether before or after our Iuſtification.</p>
            <p>Now, that which out of theſe words we conclude, doth of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie follow, but that our Aduerſaries fearing, leſt <hi>their</hi> Diana <hi>of Merits</hi> ſhould be nothing eſteemed, if they caſt not a miſt before mens eyes, to hinder from them ſeeing the cleere light of truth that ſhineth in our Doctrine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 19.25.28.</note> aſſemble as did the Siluerſmiths at the call of <hi>Demetrius,</hi> who told them, <hi>by that craft they got their goods;</hi> and with ſuch other ſpeeches, <hi>made them full of wrath,</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they cried out, ſaying, <hi>Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</hi> Euen ſo is it with vs. The Romiſh <hi>Demetrius,</hi> that getteth much by ſelling ſuch as they call good Workes, with his followers ſeeking to defend the Doctrine of Merits, cry out of that which teacheth Iuſtification by faith only, whereby they may haue much loſſe, if want of euill gotten goods may bee counted loſſe. I confeſſe, we teach, that <hi>Faith only doth iuſtifie:</hi> that is, that a true and liuely faith, wrought in our hearts by Gods Spirit, working by loue,<note place="margin">True faith only iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth.</note> fruitfull in good workes, adorned and beautified with holineſſe of life (for theſe are badges whereby to know a true faith) doth iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and acquite vs before God, ſo as wee boldly ſtand and plead not guiltie. Whereby our Aduerſaries may ſee, how vniuſtly they ſlander vs and our Doctrine, as if wee were enemies to all good Workes. And yet we only teach, that ſuch a true faith as I haue now deſcribed, without reſpect of the Workes that alwayes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companie it, doth iuſtifie, not by the Merit of this faith, but in that it is our hand whereby we apprehend and hold faſt, that Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which we haue in Chriſt, through the vnſpeakeable mercie of God.</p>
            <p>And this our Doctrine is ſo warranted in Sacred Scripture, as nothing more. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doeth often vſe excluſiue words,<note place="margin">Excluſiue words. Negatiue. Equiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent.</note> as theſe are <hi>without the Law: without Workes.</hi> Sometime plaine nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue words, <hi>Not by Workes, not by the Law.</hi> Otherwhile words e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiualent, or of ſuch like force; As, <hi>by grace, Freely.</hi> Theſe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of ſpeech when I conſider of, I cannot but like well of the good and Chriſtian counſell, giuen by <hi>Primaſius</hi> an ancient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Audi gratis, tace de Meritis. Heare</hi> (what the Apoſtle ſayth) <hi>freely, and ſpeake not a word of Merits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, therefore I reaſon for our Doctrine of Iuſtification by faith only: If Workes are not to be ioyned with faith in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17908:17"/> of Iuſtification, then faith only, euen by the confeſſion of our Aduerſaries doth iuſtifie. For our Romiſh Catholikes denie not this our Doctrine but in reſpect of workes, neyther doe they in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny their Bookes or Writings, ſeeke to match any thing with faith as cauſe of Iuſtification, but workes only: But workes are not to be ioyned with faith, in the matter of Iuſtification, as the Apoſtle moſt plainly proueth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>Know ye, that a man is not iustified by the Workes of the Law, but by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Againe, <hi>Ye are ſaued by grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>through faith, not of your ſelues, it is the gift of God, not of Workes, leſt any man ſhould boaſt himſelfe.</hi> Laſtly, theſe words to the Romanes are very effectuall.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.28.</note> 
               <hi>Therfore wee conclude, that a man is iuſtified by faith without the workes of the Law.</hi> As if he would haue ſaid, We the Apoſtles of Ieſus Chriſt, appointed to bee the Scholemaſters and Teachers of the World, vpon good ground teach this as a doctrine not to be denied, a principle in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion not to be doubted of.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Faith only</note>And howſoeuer our Aduerſaries impugne this Doctrine, and would perſwade the ſimple, that it is ſtrange, and hath no warrant: yet are we able to produce ſuch, as many hundreds of yeeres ſince, haue taught the ſame, and gathered it out of theſe words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. <hi>Origen,</hi> who liued about fourteene hundred yeeres ſince, in verie few words,<note place="margin">Orig. in Ro. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> doth twice auerre the ſame: <hi>Dixit Apoſtolus</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>fide, ſolius iuſtificationem ſufficere, ita vt credens quis tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tummodo iuſtificetur: The Apoſtle</hi> hath ſaid, <hi>that Iuſtification of faith only will ſuffice, ſo that he who beleeueth only, is iuſtified. Iſichius</hi> wrote at the leaſt a thouſand yeeres ſince, and he ſayth much like, as <hi>Origen</hi> before him:<note place="margin">Iſich. in Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>18</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gratia &amp; miſericordia, fide comprehenditur ſola, non ex operibus, vt dicit Apoſtolus: Grace and mercy is obtained by faith only, not by Workes, as Paul ſaith.</hi> We cannot then be iuſtly charged as Teachers of new Doctrine heerein, ſeeing wee affirme nothing, but that others long before vs haue taught.</p>
            <p>But, becauſe this is ſo much miſliked, as it is, and ſo ſcornefully reiected of our aduerſaries, although all truth muſt bee grounded vpon the word of truth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.18.</note> as S. <hi>Iames</hi> calleth the Word of God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther needeth it the teſtimonie of any man, which God in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures ſo plainly hath deliuered: yet for the ſatisfying of the ſimple, and the ſtopping of the ſlanderous mouthes of our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate enemies; I purpoſe to let you ſee ſuch a conſent with vs in Doctrine for this point, of Ancient Fathers and Learned Writers
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17908:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> long before our time, as in no one article or piece of doctrine, wherein our aduerſaries diſſent from vs, I ſuppoſe a greater can be ſhewed, neither mo ſeuerall Authors alleaged. So that I may well impanell for tryall of this controuerſie, two Grand-Iuries of famous men, well reported of for godlineſſe and learning among all men; many of them, and the meaneſt of them, of ſuch repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in the Church of Rome, as they are thought ſufficient to goe vpon tryall of as great a matter as this is (although it be of great importance:) And <hi>S. Paul</hi> himſelfe ſhall ſpeake for all, as you heare hee hath done, and bee Fore-man of this Iurie, for they all haue learned of him that they ſay, euen in theſe wordes, which now I intreat vpon.</p>
            <p>And firſt I will ſecond him with ſome of them,<note place="margin">Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe wordes.</note> that wrote their Commentaries vpon this Epiſtle of <hi>S. Paul</hi> to the Romanes. All I haue not, out of ſuch as I haue I will alleage, but out of euery one, one place, although out of diuers of them I might produce very many. Of <hi>Origen</hi> I haue ſpoken before, and therefore I now omit him. <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> is next, who affordeth very good choice of teſtimonies, he hath ſuch plenty.<note place="margin">Amb. in Rom. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iuſtificati ſunt gratis</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>quia nihil operantes, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vicem reddentes, Sola fide iuſtificati ſunt dono Dei: They are iuſtified freely, becauſe working nothing, neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſing, they are iuſtified by faith only by Gods gift.</hi> S. IEROME very briefly, but as plainely, writeth,<note place="margin">Hieron. in Rom. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Per ſolam fidem iuſtificat Deus: God iuſtifieth by faith only.</hi> Then haue we <hi>Sedulius,</hi> writing thus: <hi>Ad Christum veniens ſola quum credit fide ſaluatur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sedul. in Rom. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He that commeth vnto Chriſt, is ſaued by faith only, when he beleeueth.</hi> And the laſt of this ranke ſhall <hi>Primaſius</hi> be, who writeth thus,<note place="margin">Primaſ. in Rom. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Impium per ſolam fidem iuſtificat: God iuſtifieth the vngodly by faith only.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another ſort of them, whom I meane to produce in this matter,<note place="margin">Other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding other Scriptures</note> are ſuch, as expounding other places of Scripture, haue in ſuch their Commentaries taught the ſame doctrine. Among whom the firſt is <hi>Hilarie,</hi> as moſt ancient in yeeres, ſo moſt worthy to haue the firſt roome, becauſe he ſetteth downe the very wordes in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion betweene vs now:<note place="margin">Hil. in Mat. Con. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sola fides iuſtificat</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Only faith iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth.</hi> The next ſhall be <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> who, as he was next him in yeeres of all this company, ſo hee differeth very little in wordes. <hi>Ex ſola quippe fide nos ſaluauit: For by faith only he hath ſaued vs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Eph. hom. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> a man moſt famous in Gods Church for learning, and his great labours againſt Heretikes, well agreeth with the reſt,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17908:18"/> ſaying,<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſ. <hi>88</hi> Conc. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sola fides Chriſti mundat: The faith only of Chriſt cleanſeth.</hi> To whom may <hi>Cyril</hi> alſo be added, who though he haue not the ſame wordes, yet teacheth he that ſubſtance of doctrine in theſe wordes:<note place="margin">Cyril. Alex. in Iob. lib. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Per fidem; nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> non aliter ſaluamur: By faith; for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way we are ſaued.</hi> ISYCHIVS I haue before produced, I will not therefore mention him againe in this place. But venerable <hi>Bede,</hi> the glory of our North Country, ſpeaketh more plainely. <hi>Per iuſtitiam factorum nullus ſaluabitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beda in Pſ. <hi>77.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſed per ſolam iuſtitiam fidei: By righteouſneſſe of workes ſhall no man be ſaued, but by the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of faith only.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theophil. in Gal. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> After him <hi>Theophilact</hi> writeth thus: <hi>Demonſtrat (Apoſtolus) fidem vel ſolam habere iuſtificandi virtutem: The Apoſtle ſheweth, that euen only faith hath power to iuſtifie.</hi> Very well alſo, and agreeably to the reſt writeth <hi>Haimo,</hi> who liued about ſome 800. yeeres ſince:<note place="margin">Haimo in Gal. <hi>3.</hi> Bernard. in Cantic. ſer. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Fides ſola ſaluat: Faith only ſaueth.</hi> And moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably, as in many things, writeth good BERNARD. <hi>Quiſquis pro peccatis compunctus, eſurit &amp; ſitit iuſtitiam, credat in te qui iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat impium, &amp; ſolam iuſtificatus per fidem, pacem habebit apud Deum: Whoſo feeleth remorce for ſinne, and ſo doth hunger and thirſt after righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, let him beleeue in thee, who doſt iuſtifie the vngodly, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iuſtified by faith only, he ſhall haue peace with God.</hi> And <hi>Oecume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> telleth vs,<note place="margin">Oecumen. in Iam <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That</hi> ABRAHAM <hi>was an image of iuſtification by faith only, when it was imputed to him for righteouſnes that he beleeued.</hi> Then haue we <hi>Rupert,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rupert. in Reg. cap. <hi>39.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> who writeth, that <hi>ſola iuſtificare potest fides Ieſu Chriſti: The only faith of Ieſus Chriſt can iuſtifie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sundry other Fathers alſo and learned Writers we haue, who in their ſeuerall Treatiſes affirme that alſo,<note place="margin">Fathers in their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes.</note> which we out of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doe gather. To begin with <hi>Cyprian</hi> as moſt ancient: <hi>Fides tantùm prodeſt</hi> (ſaith he:) <hi>Faith only profiteth.</hi> Next vnto him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>Baſil,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cypr. l. <hi>3.</hi> ad Quir. c. <hi>42.</hi> Baſil. Hom. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> whoſe wordes are theſe: <hi>Ea demum perfecta &amp; omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moda gloriatio eſt in Deo, quandone<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> propter ſuam ipſius iuſtitiam quis extollitur, ſed agnoſcit ſe quidem vera deſtitui iuſtitia, verum ſola in Chriſtum fide iuſtificatum eſſe: That is perfit reioycing, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Lord, when a man is not proud, no not of his owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but confeſſeth himſelfe to be deſtitute thereof, and that hee is iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied only by faith in Chriſt.</hi> GREG. NAZIAN. who for the great opinion of learning, that was conceiued of him, was called <hi>the Diuine,</hi> as he was in <hi>Baſils</hi> time, ſo was he of his mind too, as theſe his wordes doe ſhew:<note place="margin">Nazian. Orat. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Confiteri Chriſtum, &amp; credat illum a mortuis ſuſcitatum eſſe &amp; ſaluaberis. Siquidem credere ſolum iuſtitia eſt: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17908:18"/> Chriſt, and beleeue that he is raiſed from the dead, and thou ſhalt be ſaued. For to beleeue only is righteouſneſſe.</hi> PAVLINVS alſo is of the ſame minde, that the reſt are, as wee may ſee in an Epiſtle, which is among <hi>S. Auguſtines</hi> Epiſtles: his wordes are,<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>58.</hi> Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Salus fide ſola quaeritur: Saluation is ſought for by faith only.</hi> This is alſo the iudgement of <hi>Ruffine,</hi> in his expoſition of the Creede, it is among <hi>Cyprians</hi> workes.<note place="margin">Ruffin. in Symbolum.</note> 
               <hi>De remiſſione peccatorum</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſufficere debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret ſola credulitas: Concerning remiſſion of ſinnes, beleeuing only ſhould ſuffice.</hi> And the reaſon of this his aſſertion is not to bee omitted. <hi>Quis enim cauſas aut rationem requirat, vbi indulgentia principalis eſt? For who will inquire after cauſes, or a reaſon, where indulgence</hi> (or pardon) <hi>is principall?</hi> THEODORET alſo, as oft in other his Treatiſes, ſo alſo in his bookes againſt the Idolatrie of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and in defence of Chriſtian Religion, writeth thus:<note place="margin">Theod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. de curat. Grae. Affect. l. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis operibus noſtris, ſed per ſolam fidem, myſtica bona conſecuti ſumus: Not by any our workes, but by faith only we haue gotten vnknowne good things.</hi> Now vnto theſe I may adde <hi>Leo</hi> a Pope, in an Epiſtle that he ſent by one called <hi>Philo,</hi> to <hi>Leo,</hi> then Emperour. It is not his 70. Epiſtle (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> vntruly quoteth the place) but 76. But his wordes are theſe: <hi>Catholica fides humanum genus ſola vinificat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leo Epi. <hi>76.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſola ſanctificat: The Catholike faith doth only quicken, only ſanctifie man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde.</hi> But <hi>Bellarmine</hi> anſwereth, that <hi>Leo</hi> in thoſe wordes ſpeaketh <hi>De fide dogmatica: Of a dogmaticall faith;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar. de Iuſtif. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> and ſuch as is oppoſed againſt Heretikes. As if he had ſaid, that the Arrian faith, or that of the Eutycheans ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſanctifie, but that faith which is true and Catholike. Be it ſo, yet he muſt needes grant, that no dogmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call faith, that is, no externall profeſſion of Religion, how earneſt in ſhew ſoeuer it is, be it alſo neuer ſo true, can quicken and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie, vntil it be as a ſeed ſowne in the heart, taking hold of Chriſt for the remiſſion of ſinnes; and ſo it, I ſay, it only giueth true life to a Chriſtian. I haue alſo read theſe very wordes, cited out of <hi>Alcuine,</hi> whom ſome call <hi>Albine;</hi> the booke, I confeſſe,<note place="margin">Alcuin. Praefat. ad Carol. Mag.</note> I haue not ſeene. But if he haue ſuch words, he ſeemeth well to approue that which <hi>Leo</hi> hath written, becauſe hee hath alleaged his very wordes without any change. I will cloze vp this ranke with one, well eſteemed of in the Church of Rome:<note place="margin">Rich. de S. Victor. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſione dubi. Apoſtoli.</note> 
               <hi>Ecce</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>habes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertè, quòd poſſit homo aliquando iuſtificari ex ſola fide, abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> legis ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: Behold, thou ſeeſt plainely, that a man may ſometime be iuſtified by faith only, without any worke of the Law.</hi> Which, ſeeing hee will
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17908:19"/> grant to be ſometime, I ſee no reaſon why he ſhould doubt, but that it is ſo alwayes. For there is but one way of iuſtifying Iew or Gentile,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22.</note> one or other, <hi>Euen the righteouſneſſe of God, by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, vnto all, and vpon all that beleeue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Chriſtian Poets.</note>There are then three ancient Chriſtian Poets, who ſing the ſame ſong, with theſe Fathers and learned Writers. <hi>Iuuencus</hi> is firſt,<note place="margin">Hier. Catal. Script. eccl. Hieron. in Mat. <hi>2.</hi> Iuueac. hiſt. Euang. l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> who liued about the 330. yeere of Grace, of whom <hi>S. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> maketh mention, and alſo citeth a Verſe out of him, in his Commentaries vpon <hi>S. Matthewes</hi> Goſpell. This <hi>Iuuencus,</hi> I ſay, hath theſe wordes: <hi>Nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vbi certa fides fuerit complexa ſalutem, non erit vlla illic anceps agitatio iuris: For when aſſured faith hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken hold of ſaluation, there will be no more doubtfull waging of Law.</hi> Not long after him was <hi>Prudentius,</hi> who in a booke, intituled <hi>Pſychomachia,</hi> wherein hee ſheweth what fights and battels the ſoule hath,<note place="margin">Prudent. pugna con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord.</note> ſpeaking of faith, writeth thus, <hi>Haec mea ſola ſalus: This faith only is my ſaluation.</hi> And I finde alleaged by that famous learned man of our time, <hi>D. Humphrey,</hi> in his anſwere to <hi>Campians</hi> firſt reaſon: the like out of one <hi>Victor Cemenſis,</hi> as I take it, but his wordes are theſe,<note place="margin">Victor.</note> writing of <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, <hi>Credidit, &amp; nudae fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei conſenſio ſola, plenam ad iuſtitiae &amp; meritireputata coronam eſt:</hi> ABRAHAM <hi>beleeued, and this conſent only of bare faith, was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to him for a full crowne of righteouſneſſe and merit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Popiſh Writers.</note>Yet haue I reſerued three great Rabbies in the Romiſh Church, for the ſhutting vp of this queſtion, who if they ſpeake, as their Fore-man hath done, and many other before them, I hope, we ſhal be found not guiltie of errour, much leſſe of hereſie. The firſt of this company is <hi>Gratian,</hi> the very ſtore-houſe of their Canon Law, who very plainely affirmeth,<note place="margin">Diſt. <hi>2.</hi> de Poenit. cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas eſt a q.</note> that <hi>fidei ſoli vaenia promittitur: To faith only is pardon promiſed.</hi> And a little after, <hi>Fide ſola peccata relaxantur: By faith only, ſinnes are remitted.</hi> If any man anſwere, that he there telleth vs but what <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith: true; but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all he alleageth it, not as miſliking, but as approuing it as ſound doctrine. After him commeth <hi>Peter Lombard,</hi> though equall in time (for it is ſaid that <hi>Gratian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Danaeus in Com. in Lombard. in prolego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menis, c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Lombard,</hi> and <hi>Petrus Comestor,</hi> were all brethren, and the baſtard children of a Nunne) <hi>Lombard,</hi> I ſay, Biſhop of Paris, whoſe authority in the Church of Rome, was like that <hi>Pythagoras</hi> had among his Schollers, among whom it was enough, to ſay, The Maſter ſaith it. His writings are in ſuch account with them, that they are the very ground of Popiſh or
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17908:19"/> Schoole diuinitie. In ſo much, as ſince hee wrote his bookes of Sentences, very many by their Commentaries haue laboured to explane him, ſtudying ſomtime to make him agree with himſelfe, ſometime with that the Church Romiſh hath formerly taught. <hi>Lambertus Danaeus,</hi> in the place before alleaged, reckoneth at the leaſt 37. or 38. who haue taken ſuch paines, and yet as not hauing reckoned all, referreth them, who are deſirous to know of mo, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Trithemius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This great Doctor of the chaire for Schoole-diuinitie, in a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face he writeth before his Commentaries vpon <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, in the very latter end thereof, gathering a briefe and ſumme of the former part of <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to the Romanes, hath theſe wordes: <hi>Pluribus modis oſtendit iustitiam &amp; ſalutem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lombard. Praefat in Comment. in Epi. Paul.</note> 
               <hi>aequè Iudaeis &amp; Gentibus eſſe, non per legem ſed per fidem Ieſu Christi, vt à lege eos tollat, &amp; in ſola fide Christi eos constituat: The Apostle many wayes proueth, that righteouſneſſe and ſaluation is both to Iewes and Gentiles alike, not by the Law, but by faith of Ieſus Christ, that he may with-draw them from the Law, and ſettle them in the only faith of Christ.</hi> And after, in the very beginning of his expoſition, vpon the third Chapter of the Epiſtle vnto the Philippians:<note place="margin">Lombard. in Epiſt. ad Philip. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Contra Pſeudo-apostolos eos monuit, ne legalia ab eis recipiant, ſed fidem Chriſti ſolam ſufficere cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant: Againſt falſe Apoſtles he hath admoniſhed them, that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not of them precepts of the Law, but beleeue that the only faith of Chriſt ſufficeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet haue we the Doctor of Doctors behinde, that Angellical Doctor (for ſo they call him) whoſe wordes at Rome are Oracles, and his writings, with too many, haue more credit, then the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures. Yet in this, I beleeue, he will proue a Lutheran or Caluiniſt, I know not whether, but ſure I am a <hi>Paulinist.</hi> Yee ſhall heare his owne words, that you may know I wrong him not. <hi>Moralium legitimus vſus eſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>vt homo non attribuat eis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tho. Aquin. <hi>1.</hi> Tim. <hi>1.</hi> Ier. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quam quod in eis continetur. Data eſt lex vt cognoſcatur peccatum, Rom.</hi> 7. <hi>Concupiſcentiam neſciebam, niſi lex diceret: Non concupiſces, quod dicitur in decalogo.</hi> Notable good counſell it is, which in theſe wordes hee giueth, and ſound and Chriſtian inſtruction, which I would it were well marked. <hi>The lawfull vſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of the morall precepts is, when a man aſcribeth not any thing to them, but what in them is contayned. The Law is giuen, that ſinne might bee knowne,</hi> Rom. 7. <hi>I knew not lust, except the Law had ſaid, Thou ſhalt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17908:20"/> not lust, as is ſaid in the Decalog.</hi> Now marke the concluſion, which he hereupon inferreth. <hi>Non eſt ergo in eis ſpes iuſtificationis, ſed in ſola fide,</hi> Rom. 3. <hi>Arbitramur hominem iustificari per fidem, abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peribus legis: Therefore, there is not in them</hi> (the precepts of the Law) <hi>any hope of iuſtification, but in faith only,</hi> Rom. 3. <hi>We conclude that a man is iuſtified by faith, without the workes of the Law.</hi> I haue the more carefully ſet downe his words, becauſe they are ſo plaine and pregnant for vs. For firſt, he teacheth that the lawfull vſe of the morall Law, is to let vs ſee our ſinne (not to ſeeke for iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by it, as after he ſheweth.) And why ſhould wee bee taught this, if not to driue vs vnto Chriſt? Then alſo he affirmeth, that there is no hope of ſaluation therein, but in faith only. And that which doth much contradict our now Romiſh Catholikes, he ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth this doctrine of Iuſtification by faith only, euen out of theſe wordes of <hi>Paul,</hi> as we doe. How now can we be Heretikes, and your Angellical Doctor a Catholike! No, no, hee writeth as plainely for Iuſtification by faith only, as any of vs. It is high time the purgers of mens writings ſhould be ſet on work, to mend their <hi>Index Expurgatorius,</hi> that <hi>Thomas</hi> may bee taught to ſpeake otherwiſe then thus, or elſe he will marre all, for he ſpeaketh here not Romiſh.</p>
            <p>For to make it more plaine, what hee thinketh elſewhere too, concerning iuſtification by workes, when duly and indifferently he conſidereth of the word it ſelfe, and examineth that he writeth by the true touch-ſtone, one place more, out of the ſaid <hi>Thomas,</hi> I truſt, ſhall not be thought tedious. Expounding the wordes of <hi>S. Paul</hi> to the Galathians,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>As many as are of the workes of the Law, are vnder the curſe,</hi> He ſheweth, the Apoſtle ſpeaketh here of all workes,<note place="margin">Aquin. in Gal. <hi>3.</hi> Lect. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Ceremoniall, or Morall. <hi>Opera enim non ſunt cauſa quòd aliquis ſit iuſtus apud Deum, ſed potiùs executiones &amp; manifeſtationes iuſtitiae. Nam nullus per opera iuſtificatur apud Deum, ſed per habitum fidei, non quidem acquiſitum, ſed infuſum. Et ideo quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ex operibus legis iuſtificari quaerunt, ſub maledicto ſunt, quia per ea peccata non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouentur, nec aliquis quo ad Deum iuſtificatur, ſed per habitum fidei charitate informatum: For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>workes are not the cauſe why a man is iuſt before God, but the executions rather, or manifeſtations of iuſtice. For by workes is no man iuſtified before God, but by the habit of faith, and that not gotten, but giuen. Whoſoeuer then by the workes of the Law, ſeeke to be iuſtified, are vnder the curſe, becauſe by works our
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17908:20"/> ſinnes are not put away, neyther is any iuſtified before God, but by faith beautified with loue.</hi> Theſe two ſentences of <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Aquine</hi> being duly weighed, doe as plainely auow Iuſtification by faith only, and diſproue Iuſtification by Workes and our owne Merits, as any thing we doe ſay or write: inſomuch, as if he were aliue, I make no doubt, but he ſhould be forced eyther to recant, or would be accounted a <hi>Caluiniſt,</hi> hee followeth ſo truly the trace of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine herein.</p>
            <p>But, what if our Countriman <hi>Stapleton</hi> bee of this minde too? I know that (if hee were aliue) he would not ſay ſo for any thing, he hath alwayes beene ſo peſtilent and peruerſe an enemie to the ſame, calling the Doctrine of Iuſtification by faith only,<note place="margin">Stap. Antid. in Act. <hi>15.10.</hi> Antid. in Ro. <hi>3.</hi> v. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>A moſt wicked and moſt pestilent Doctrine.</hi> Yea, &amp; elſewhere too, he is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better perſwaded thereof, but ſayth, <hi>It is impious, and full of ſhame:</hi> ſo ſhamefully doth this impious wretch, write of this moſt comfortable Doctrine. But we will not moue him to ſay it plainly: wee will not ſtand vpon termes; ſo hee teach the ſubſtance of the Doctrine, we will beare with him. And with a little helpe hee will be brought to that. We will but lend him a <hi>Maior</hi> propoſition, much like that which I vſed in the beginning of this diſcourſe of Iuſtification by faith only, and he will fit himſelfe of a <hi>Minor,</hi> and ſo iumpe with vs in Doctrine. If the Apoſtle exclude from Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication all workes, ſo as they haue no power to iuſtifie, then faith only doth iuſtifie: but he excludeth all workes from hauing power to iuſtifie: therefore faith only iuſtifieth. The <hi>Maior</hi> I haue ſhewed before, is not to bee denyed of any Papiſts, becauſe that they ſeeke not to ioyne with faith any thing in the matter of Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, but only workes. As for my <hi>Minor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stap. Antid. in Act. <hi>3.10.</hi>
               </note> it is granted by <hi>Stapleton</hi> in the words before alleadged, that <hi>the Apoſtle excludeth Workes from hauing power to iuſtifie abſolutely, that is, to forgiue ſinnes.</hi> Thus haue we one more on our ſide then we hoped for, and ſo may be bold (I truſt) to conclude.</p>
            <p>Now, although this cloud of witneſſes is ſufficient, I hope, to cleere vs from any ſiniſter imputation of euill dealing, as if wee would teach that is ſtrange, and not heard of, but of late dayes: yet we haue in this point, a better teſtimonie then all men can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord vs. For the aſſurance of this Doctrine is this, that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt ſealeth vp this confidence in our hearts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16.</note> and <hi>Gods Spirit beareth witneſſe with our Spirit, that wee are the children of God, and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17908:21"/> hauing receiued the Sprit of adoption, we are bold to cry, Abba Father.</hi> This, this, I ſay, is the argument that more perſwadeth the children of God, then all that men can bring. This argument did ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince euen the very conſcience of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>That the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Law was</hi> (as I may ſo ſay) <hi>but lothſome to him, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that righteouſnes which he longed after by Chriſt.</hi> This righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe whoſo hath a true feeling of, he doth but laugh to ſcorne the idle diſputations of them, that ſeeke to proue it muſt bee had by Workes.</p>
            <p>But I am not ignorant, how our Aduerſaries doe what in them lyeth, to elude the teſtimonies of God and all good men, and as much as they can, to dimme the verie light of our conſciences; that wee ſhould not ſee this comfort.<note place="margin">Bell. de Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtif. l. <hi>1.</hi> c <hi>25</hi> Annot. in Iam. <hi>2.24.</hi>
               </note> And therefore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſeemeth to make ſome anſwer to ſome few places alleaged out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Fathers againſt them. So doe the Rhemiſts too, in their Annotations vpon the new Teſtament. But all in vaine: the Sunne of truth ſhineth ſo cleere, that all they can doe, is not ſufficient to dimme the light thereof. For this word, <hi>Faith only,</hi> being ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly vſed as it is, teacheth vs, that nothing but faith is that which by our Sauiour Chriſt iuſtifieth. For it only cannot be ſaid to doe it, if eyther Law of Ceremonies, or of the Commandements, the workes eyther of the vnrighteous or of the faithfull bee ioyned with it. And therefore, though our Aduerſaries would ſometime exclude one thing from iuſtifying, ſometime another: yet ſo long as they exclude not all, but faith in Chriſt Ieſus, from being cauſe of our Iuſtification, they ſeeke but to deceiue vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aug de fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de &amp; ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribuc. <hi>14. Good workes neceſſarie when we are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi> Aug. de fide &amp; operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note>Yet I denie not, but workes, as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>doe follow him that alreadie is iuſtified, though they goe not before him that is to be iuſtified.</hi> For they are (as a little before I ſaid out of <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quine</hi>) the execution and manifeſtation of our righteouſneſſe, but no cauſes therof. In which ſence, the Fathers very often, eſpecially Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in many places hauing ſhewed plentifully out of the Apoſtle, <hi>That we are iuſtified by faith without the workes of the Law:</hi> Yet withall, he giueth vs to vnderſtand, that, <hi>Hoc non a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, vt percepta ac profeſſa fide, opera iuſtitiae contemnantur: hee goeth not about thereby to make vs contemne the workes of righteouſneſſe, we once hauing receiued and profeſſed faith. No, we (when once we are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified) are Gods workemanſhip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>created in Christ Ieſus vnto good works, which God hath ordained that we ſhould walke in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:17908:21"/>
            <p>Againe, they tell vs, ſome of the Fathers ſpeake of faith as it is Dogmaticall, for our profeſſion or Religion, and that in ſuch ſence only they affirme, <hi>Faith only to iuſtifie,</hi> becauſe it is the true, and not a falſe faith that muſt ſaue. Of which I ſayd ſomewhat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when I alleadged the words of <hi>Leo,</hi> for confirmation of our Doctrine. But yet ſomewhat more to explane the matter, wee muſt conſider that faith hath two reſpects:<note place="margin">Outward Doctrine.</note> The one as it is an outward thing which is taught, or wee may reade of it in Bookes. That pierceth the eares, it hath alſo conſent of the minde and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, when we yeeld to the truth therof. But this; though a true faitht yet vntill it be planted in the heart and beleeued, iuſtifieth not. As for example, the Deuill may and did know the true faith, as when he ſaid, <hi>Ieſus, the Sonne of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.29. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.24.</note> 
               <hi>what haue wee to doe with thee?</hi> Againe, <hi>What haue we to doe with thee, Ieſus of Nazareth? art thou come to deſtroy vs? I know what thou art, That holy ome of God.</hi> We reade alſo elſewhere in Saint <hi>Marke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 3.11</note> 
               <hi>When the vncleane Spirits ſaw Chriſt, they fell downe before him and cryed, ſaying. Thou art the Sonne of God.</hi> And Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſayth plainely,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>The Deuils beleeue that there is one God and tremble.</hi> But our Aduerſaries will grant, that although it is a Catholicke faith that the Deuils haue: yet it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth them not to ſaluation. That faith in Chriſt Ieſus doth iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie is a true faith, that is a true Doctrine; yet no doubt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged of many, that ſhall neuer find with comfort the ſweetneſſe thereof. But when this perſwaſion is well rooted in the heart,<note place="margin">Inward aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance.</note> ſo that it maketh vs to reſt and repoſe our ſelues vpon God, which we call beleeuing in God, then doth it iuſtifie. Thus then, although it is moſt true, that it muſt be a Catholike, not an Hereticall faith that ſaueth: yet euen that true &amp; Catholike faith doth not quicken, it doth not ſanctifie, or iuſtifie, vnleſſe to our endleſſe comfort, we receiue the ſame into the heart. And ſo as the Catholike faith is only auaileable: ſo vntill it be receiued into the heart, it helpeth not, and then it only iuſtifieth.</p>
            <p>But many things are out of the Scripture obiected againſt this Doctrine, whereby the ſimple, and ſuch as are not acquainted with the Word,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.14.</note> neyther <hi>by long cuſtome haue their wits exerciſed to diſcerne both good and euill,</hi> as the Apoſtle to the Hebrewes ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, may ſoone be deceiued. For to ſuch as haue not iudgement to trye Metals, euen Tinne will ſeeme Siluer, and Copper Gold; becauſe in colour they are ſomewhat like. To ſay nothing of ſuch
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17908:22"/> places, it may bee dangerous in theſe our euill dayes, leſt thereby ſome that deſire to know the truth, by the name of Scripture, wreſted to a wrong ſence, may be led into errour. And yet to ſpeak of euery particular place alleadged would bee verie tedious, for they are many. I haue therefore thought good to draw them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome few heads, and ſo anſwering their principall allegations, it will not be hard to iudge of all others alſo.</p>
            <p>I will beginne with ſuch Scriptures as ſeeme to aſcribe <hi>Worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto men.</hi> For out of them doth <hi>Bellarmine</hi> thus gather, <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num eſſe praemio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Iuſtific. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>ca.</hi> 2, 3 What wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe in men. <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; mereri praemium idem ſunt: To bee worthy of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and to deſerue a reward is all one.</hi> And to proue this worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in men, he alleadgeth foure places. The firſt is taken out of the Booke of <hi>Wiſedome, God tryed them and found them worthie of himſelfe.</hi> The Booke from whence this teſtimonie is taken, is knowne not to be Canonicall Scriptures, and therfore of no ſuch credit in Gods Church, as that vpon places out of it, wee may ground any Article of Religion. And this anſwere might ſerue ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie well to this obiection. But yet the words themſelues doe not of neceſſity proue merit or worthineſſe of the workes that we doe. And that firſt in reſpect of the perſon that trieth, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo in regard of them that are tryed. He that tryeth his ſeruants, is (I know) wiſe enough to examine and ſpye faults, iuſt alſo to puniſh them: But he is alſo content to couer with the righteouſnes of his Sonne our faults, and to hide our iniquities, not beholding vs, as in our ſelues we are ſinners,<note place="margin">Who are found righteous or worthy. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24.</note> but as we are in Chriſt righteous. Then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo who are they that being tryed are found righteous? Euen they whoſe debt Chriſt hath paid, for whoſe ſinnes hee hath ſatisfied, <hi>and ſealed vp,</hi> as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſayth, that they may bee no more remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, <hi>Whoſe iniquitie he hath reconciled, to bring in euerlaſting righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</hi> Of ſuch we ſee who bring with them nothing whereby they ſhould be found worthy, but haue all from Chriſt, it is ſaid, <hi>he found them worthy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other two places hee bringeth for which wee are much behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to him, becauſe by them we may learne how to anſwere ſuch teſtimonies, as ſeeme to aſcribe worthineſſe vnto men. One is out of the anſwere that Chriſt maketh vnto the Sadduces (a Sect which thought there is no reſurrection) who thought to intrappe him in a ſubtile queſtion. The queſtion was of one woman that married ſeuen husbands, who all dying, they would know whoſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17908:22"/> wife ſhe ſhould be at the Reſurrection? To whom Chriſt anſweres thus, <hi>They who ſhall be counted worthy to enioy that world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.35.</note> 
               <hi>and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection from the dead, neither marry wiues, nor are married.</hi> The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is much like this:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>That yee may be counted worthy of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, for which yee alſo ſuffer,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Paul</hi> to the Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians. Now, who knoweth not that we may bee counted worthy of that, which in due conſideration we cannot be worthy of? So, that they are accounted worthy, proueth not that they are worthy indeed, as ſhall, God willing, by and by plainely appeare.</p>
            <p>The fourth place then muſt ſerue the turne, or elſe nothing is ſaid. That is, the wordes of our Sauiour Chriſt of ſome of Sardi: <hi>They ſhall walke with me in white: for they are worthy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3.4.</note> As if Chriſt had ſaid, they ſhall triumph with me, <hi>or raigne in glory,</hi> and life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting, for they are worthy. But what are they worthy in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their worke, or for the merit thereof? For if not, it helpeth not our Aduerſaries.</p>
            <p>And that neither they, nor any other,<note place="margin">No man worthy of eternall life, but Chriſt.</note> that is conceiued (as we all are) of vncleane ſeede, can be worthy in reſpect of workes: <hi>I proue thus.</hi> No man is worthy of eternall life, in reſpect of works, but hee who can fulfill the Law; but no man can fulfill the Law: therefore, by their workes no man can be worthy of eternall life. My firſt Propoſition I proue thus. God himſelfe ſaith to his people of Iſrael: <hi>If thou keepe my Statutes, thou ſhalt liue in them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 18.5.</note> In which wordes, as we ſee a promiſe of life, ſo muſt we obſerue the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of keeping Gods ſtatutes, if we will looke to be partakers of the promiſe. And no doubt the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul,</hi> out of theſe and ſuch like words hath learned, that which he teacheth vs of the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, which is of the Law: <hi>The man that doth theſe things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Deut</hi> 27.26 <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſhal liue thereby.</hi> But if the condition bee not obſerued, then marke what followeth, <hi>Curſed is euery man, that continueth not in all the wordes of this Law to doe them.</hi> This continuance in doing the Law, and keeping the Statutes of God, teacheth vs neither to be idle, nor euill occupied, and that wee muſt not ſwarue, either to the right hand or left, leauing the right path of Gods Law at any time. For <hi>S. Iames</hi> hath truly out of this place gathered,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.10.</note> that <hi>who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhall keepe the whole Law, and yet faileth in one point, is guilty of all.</hi> Not becauſe, whoſo breaketh one Commandement, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all. A thiefe, in that he is a thiefe, is not a murderer, or adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer: but the meaning is, he is guilty of tranſgreſſion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17908:23"/> cannot bee ſaued by the Law. If then eternall life be promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to them only, that keepe the whole Law, as is proued, much leſſe ſhall it be merited by any that fulfill not the ſame.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Minor,</hi> or ſecond Propoſition is, that no man can fulfill the Law. For confirmation whereof, I minde rather to point vnto ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments,<note place="margin">We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not perfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fulfill the Law.</note> then any way to dilate them. Firſt therefore, it is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection belonging only to Chriſt, to keepe the whole Law. He on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was without ſinne, becauſe he neuer did tranſgreſſe: Hee only could offer the ſacrifice of perfect and holy obedience, ſo that (in this reſpect) hee only could make the atonement betweene God and vs. As for his Apoſtles (though, no doubt, good men) yet they prayed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.5. <hi>Mar.</hi> 9.24.</note> as they had good cauſe: <hi>Increaſe our faith. Helpe our vnbeliefe.</hi> And our Sauiour himſelfe taught them, and in them, the perfecteſt that euer was,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.26.</note> to pray, <hi>Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes.</hi> Our imperfections then being ſo many, and ſo great, <hi>Such a high Prieſt it became vs to haue, as is holy, harmeleſſe, vndefiled, ſeparate from ſinners, made higher then the heauens.</hi> For but by ſuch a Mediator, our ſinnes are ſo great, as that wee neuer could haue beene recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God, becauſe we are farre from keeping the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience teacheth this.</note>Secondly, our owne conſciences will ſo teſtifie with me herein, and againſt our ſelues, that, I hope, I neede not produce much proofe hereof. Let vs but examine our ſelues by that rule, which the Author of all truth gaue vnto ſome, who would get (as our Papiſts ſay they can doe) eternall life by doing: by which hee meant they ſhould trie and examine themſelues.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.25.</note> 
               <hi>Maſter</hi> (ſaith a certaine expounder of the Law) <hi>what ſhall I doe to inherit eternall life?</hi>
               <note place="margin">26.27.</note> 
               <hi>And hee ſaid to him, What is written in the Law? How readeſt thou? And hee anſwered, Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thine heart, with all thy ſoule, and with all thy ſtrength, and with all thy thought,</hi>
               <note place="margin">28.</note> 
               <hi>and thy neighbour as thy ſelfe. Then he anſwered him, Thou haſt ſaid right, doe this, and thou ſhalt liue.</hi> If, I ſay, we examine our ſelues, and trie our wayes by this rule (which is a very true rule, and cannot deceiue) we will, no doubt, acknowledge our mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold tranſgreſſions. For it is impoſſible that fleſh and bloud, ſo long as it hath within it this bitter roote of corruption (which whileſt here we liue, will neuer leaue vs) ſhould ſo abandon the loue of our ſelues, and our owne delights, that thereby our loue of God ſhould be nothing hindered. If we conſider of our beſt workes, we ſhall not finde ſuch alacrity and cheerefulneſſe in our
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17908:23"/> ſelues, as is fit; neither in the worke ſuch reſpect to Gods will and glory; as wee ought to haue. So that our conſcience muſt needes tell vs, that, becauſe <hi>we are conceiued of vncleane ſeede,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.4.</note> 
               <hi>no man can make vs cleane:</hi> and therefore we muſt ſing that ſong that they did, who thus ſay, <hi>We haue beene as an vncleane thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 64.6.</note> 
               <hi>and all our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe as filthy clouts.</hi> And if we make tryall of our loue to our Neighbour, he whoſe charity among vs moſt aboundeth, will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue himſelfe to be of his minde, who ſaid, <hi>Proximus egomet mihi: I am neereſt neighbour to mine owne ſelfe.</hi> So ſhall we be found farre ſhort of the duty we owe, either to God or Man. Theſe things are ſo plaine to ſuch as haue any feeling conſciences, as that I need not ſtand vpon proofe hereof.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the confeſſions of all the godly,<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of the godly. <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.8.</note> will teach vs what wee may thinke of our obedience, and fulfilling the Law. <hi>Iob</hi> was a good man: <hi>None was like him vpon the earth, an vpright and iuſt man, one that feared God, and eſchewed euill.</hi> Yet good <hi>Iob,</hi> as in ſundry other places he confeſſeth himſelfe to be guiltie, ſo in theſe wordes: <hi>If I would iuſtifie my ſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 9.20.</note> 
               <hi>mine owne mouth would condemne me: If I would be perfit, he ſhall iudge me wicked.</hi> As if he had ſaid, If I would goe about to cleere my ſelfe, I cannot doe it, I muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my tranſgreſſion.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> was <hi>a man according to Gods owne heart,</hi> as <hi>Samuel</hi> reporteth: yet, he of himſelfe, and all other, ſaith, <hi>If thou, O Lord, ſtraitly marke our iniquities, O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.3.</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall abide it?</hi> That is, none can ſtand before thee, to iuſtifie himſelfe, if thou pry into their liues to examine their tranſgreſſions. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of the Lord calleth DANIEL <hi>a man of deſires,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.23.</note> God ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in him, and loued him: yet he in that notable prayer that he maketh for the deliuerance of Gods people, now that the 70. yeeres of their captiuity were expired, as it were, to put God in minde of his promiſe of deliuerance, confeſſeth not only the ſins of their Fathers, of their Princes, and of the People;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.5, 6, 7, 8, 10, 11.</note> but wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth himſelfe in that number too, acknowledging that to them belonged nothing but ſhame and confuſion; to God only mercy and forgiueneſſe. <hi>Paul,</hi> we all ſay, was a good man alſo, <hi>taken vp into the, third heauen, and heard wordes which cannot be ſpoken,</hi> which <hi>are not poſſible for man to vtter:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.21.</note> Yet this heauenly man <hi>found by the Law, that when he would doe good, euill was preſent with him:</hi> whereby it came to paſſe,<note place="margin">19.</note> that <hi>he did not the good thing which hee would, but the euill that he would not, that did he,</hi> as a little before,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17908:24"/> the ſame Apoſtle hath complayned. To be ſhort, <hi>S. Iames</hi> was an Apoſtle of our Sauiour Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.1.</note> whom he tooke to be one of the witneſſes of his Transfiguration, a faithfull ſeruant of God: yet of himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.2.</note> as well as of other his brethren, he hath ſaid, <hi>In mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis offendimus omnes: We all offend in many things.</hi> Wee, I ſay, that are choſen of God, we the Apoſtles of Ieſus Chriſt, who haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the holy Ghoſt in ſome good meaſure, who are aided and guided by the grace of God, we all, I ſay, offend in many things. Such confeſſions of the godly, haue imboldened the worthy lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Fathers,<note place="margin">Hieron. in Gal. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> to ſay after them as doth HIEROME, <hi>Nemo legem ſeruat: No man keepeth the Law.</hi> But of that ſort I will bring no mo teſtimonies.<note place="margin">Aquin. in Gal. <hi>3.</hi> Lect. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> The Angellicall Doctor ſhall ſpeake for all: <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plere totam legem eſt impoſſibile: It is a thing vnp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſible to fulfill the whole Law.</hi> And thus the premiſſes being proued, this concluſion doth follow, that in reſpect of workes no man is worthy.</p>
            <p>But becauſe Chriſt ſaith of ſome of Sardi, that they are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,<note place="margin">Worthy, how. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4.</note> there is, no doubt, a worthineſſe in Gods ſeruants, although in reſpect of merits wee iuſtly deny it. Therefore, Gods children are ſaid to be <hi>worthy, firſt</hi> in reſpect of their election, in that <hi>God hath choſen them before the foundation of the world:</hi> eſpecially, ſeeing <hi>we are choſen in Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">11.</note> in whom only we are found worthy. For we who in our ſelues are not, yet in him are found worthy. The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation hereof made the Apoſtle not to make reckoning but of this only,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>That he might be found in Chriſt, not hauing his owne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt.</hi> Seeing then we haue all our worthineſſe from Chriſt, that we may more earneſtly ſeeke to him, it is needfull that with all the godly we acknowledge our owne vnworthineſſe. Now, true it is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30.</note> that <hi>whom God hath predeſtinated</hi> (and choſen to be his) <hi>he alſo calleth</hi> (not only externally by outward meanes, but inwardly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by his grace) <hi>and whom he calleth, he alſo iuſtifieth; and whom he iuſtifieth, he alſo glorifieth:</hi> but yet our corruption being ſuch, as will not ſuffer vs ſincerely to follow our calling, and walke wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of our profeſſion, our worthineſſe in this reſpect will be found but vnworthineſſe, but as it is ſupplied by that worthineſſe of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Hier. ad Cleſiphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</note> Let vs therefore harken to that <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Haec homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus ſola perfectio eſt, ſi imperfectos ſe eſſe nouerint: This is the only perfection of men, if they know they are vnperfect.</hi> And ſo may we well ſay of our worthineſſe: Herein we only are found worthy, if we
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17908:24"/> confeſſe our owne vnworthines. For as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writeth,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Spirit. &amp; lit. cap. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>In ea quae perficienda eſt iuſtitia ille multùm profecit, qui quàm longè ſit à perfectione iuſtitiae proficiendo cognouit: Hee hath much profited in this life, in that righteouſneſſe that is to bee perfited, who by profiting knoweth how much he wanteth of perfection of righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another obiection they haue out of ſuch teſtimonies, as teach that <hi>God ſhall reward euery man according to his worke.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.27 <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Reue.</hi> 22.12 <hi>Bell. de Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtific. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 2 <hi>Aug. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 13 How the godly are rewarded according to workes.</note> Of which ſort the Scripture affordeth vs diuers. And out of thoſe wordes, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> draweth this Doctrine. <hi>Secundum opera ſua, id eſt, vt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera merentur, According to his workes, that is, as his workes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue:</hi> I might anſwer him with that golden ſaying of Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, Vae hominum vitae etiam ladabili, ſi remota miſericordia diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutias eam: Woe to the life of man that is commendable, if thou (Lord) ſetting mercie aſide doe ſift the ſame.</hi> But that the abſurditie of his aſſertion may the rather appeare, it is needfull, that if the reward be giuen according to the merit of the worke, there ſhould bee ſome equalitie of proportion, betweene the worke and the reward it meriteth. But what proportion can there be betweene workes ſo vnperfect as before I haue ſhewed ours to bee, and that eternall glorie, which is ſo great and excellent a reward, that the Apoſtle deſcribeth it in theſe wordes: <hi>The things which eye hath not ſeene,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>eare hath not heard, neyther can enter into the heart of man, God hath prepared for them that loue him?</hi> Howſoeuer therefore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> dareth affirme;<note place="margin">Bell. de. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtific. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That non requiritur abſoluta aequaelitas inter meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum &amp; praemium, a perfit equalitie is not requiſite betweene merit and the reward</hi> (which thing he indeed barely affirmeth, without any one teſtimonie of Scripture, or ſentence of Fathers) yet dare I boldly pronounce, that if any man ſaith, that eternall life is giuen as workes deſerue, and yet that there is no proportion betweene eternall life, and the worke, hee ſpeaketh moſt abſurdly, making merit no merit, and deſeruing no deſeruing, whereas in all reaſon and learning, how much a worke wanteth of the equalitie with the reward which is to be giuen for doing it, ſo much it lacketh of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riting that reward. Very well, therefore S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> after he hath ſhewed, <hi>That mens merits are not ſuch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. Serm. <hi>1.</hi> de An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunt.</note> 
               <hi>that eternall life is of right due to them, or that God ſhould doe wrong if he ſo giue it not, becauſe euen our merits are Gods gifts, and therefore, we are rather bound to God for them, then he to vs,</hi> asketh this queſtion: <hi>Quid ſunt merita omnia ad tantam gloriam? What are all merits to ſo great glory?</hi> As if he had
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17908:25"/> ſaid, There is no proportion, no equalitie. This then which <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> heerein hath taught, is as abſurd, as if a man ſhould af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that hee doth not ſell twelue penny-worth of ware or doe twelue penny-worth of worke, muſt be deemed to haue truly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued twelue pence. I trow, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would not well like of ſuch penny-worthes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Not as workes merit.</note>One other argument I will produce, which plainely enough confuteth that which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſayth, that <hi>According to the worke,</hi> muſt be expounded, <hi>as the worke meriteth.</hi> Conſider of the Parable of the Labourers in the Vineyard,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.1.3.5.6,</note> whereof ſome went to their labour at the dawning of the day, others at the third houre, but ſome were not called to worke, before the ſixt or ninth houres, yea other about Sunne-ſetting, that is at the eleuenth houre. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Vineyard, when euen was come, ſent for the Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and as hee promiſed to the firſt, paid to euerie one a pennie. But they who came firſt,<note place="margin">12.</note> pleaded that they had borne the burden and heat of the day, and therefore thought as our Papiſts doe, they deſerued more then the reſt. But the maſter of the Vineyard anſwered, they had their due, and what hee promiſed; if hee gaue other more, that hindred not them. Now, I would that our Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Catholikes would anſwere truly to this queſtion, If paiment ſhould haue beene made according to the merit of the worke, who deſerued moſt? I ſuppoſe they will anſwere (for otherwiſe they cannot truly anſwere) that they who came firſt to their labour, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued beſt payment. Yet, wee ſee the laſt had as much as they. Therefore it is plaine, payment was not made to them, nor ſhalbe to vs, as our worke meriteth, but according to promiſe. For eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one had his pennie.<note place="margin">Hill. in Mat. Can.</note> 
               <hi>Merces quidem nulla eſt ex dono, quia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur ex opere: ſed gratuitam Deus omnibus ex fidei iuſtificatione do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">20.</note> 
               <hi>There is no wages of gift</hi> (ſayth <hi>Hilarie) for it is due by the worke: but God hath giuen a free (reward) vnto all by Iustification of faith.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the Goſpell. <hi>Proſper de vocat. Gent. lib. c.</hi> 17.</note> Thereby prouing that <hi>this penny was not as wages, but a free reward,</hi> not for the worke but giuen in promiſe. Notably there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſayth <hi>Proſper</hi> (who wrote about that time, Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did) who gathereth out of this parable, <hi>Operarios accepiſſe donum gratiae, non mercedem operis; that theſe workemen receiued a gift of grace, not a reward or wages for their worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Bellarmine</hi> contending for merits, would faine remoue this blocke out of the way. Hee feareth leſt ſome of his friends ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17908:25"/> thereon, ſhould reele from the Romiſh Church. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore out of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and others telleth vs, that <hi>denarius diurnus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bell. de Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtific. li. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>16:</hi> &amp; li. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>this penny for the day worke, is aequalitas aeternitatis, non gloriae, equae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of eternitie, not of glorie.</hi> But our controuerſie is not what this penny is, but in what reſpect it is giuen, whether for the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the worke or not? If he ſay for the merit of the worke, the Parable is againſt his opinion therein. If he ſay it is of promiſe, as elſewhere he ſeemeth to affirme, wee haue that we ſeeke.<note place="margin">Bell. de Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Wee ſee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the whole penny giuen to them, who had not laboured the whole day: and the Lord himſelfe ſheweth in theſe words, I will giue to him as to thee, &amp;c. that this was done not of dutie, but of liberalitie.</hi> Heere our aduerſary confeſſeth, the reward not to be as the labour merited. Therefore to omit that needleſſe queſtion what this pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie is, let vs heere remember, that it is not giuen for the worthines of the worke. For <hi>Bellarmines</hi> anſwere ſeemeth to mee much like as if I aske which way I may goe to London, and he anſwere me it is a faire Citie. Seeing then the reward is of mercie, and not of merit, let not vs by aſcribing that to our workes, which is giuen freely in grace, <hi>be vnthankefull vnto him, who ſo loued vs that he dyed for vs,</hi> as Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> exhorteth vs, yeelding this reaſon:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierom</hi> vpon <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecta eſt gratia, ſi mihi ſola non ſufficit, Grace is but caſt away, if it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffice me not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it is plaine, I truſt, that, <hi>According to the work</hi> is not as our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries ſay, <hi>As the worke meriteth.</hi> But becauſe many, euen among Gods people, delighted rather in outward ſhew of godlineſſe, then in the truth thereof, contenting themſelues to bring their offering to the Prieſt, to weare (with comming to the Temple) the paue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods houſe, without any true deuotion, to performe ſome outward workes in obſeruing dayes and times, and dyet and ſuch like; theſe words teach vs, that the All-ſeeing eye is not deceiued with ſuch counterfeit holines, but he looketh more narrowly vnto the worke it ſelfe. Wherein he firſt beholdeth the fountaine, from whence it floweth, and the root from whence it ſpringeth. For as a filthy fountaine cannot yeeld wholſome waters, nor an euil tree bring forth good fruit, as our Sauiour Chriſt ſayth;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.18.</note> ſo cannot a man that lyeth in his naturall corruption of the olde man, doe any thing that ſhall bee acceptable vnto God. The workes that come from the Spirit of Regeneration, hee rewardeth in mercie: the workes that are only from the olde ADAM, what ſhew of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17908:26"/> holineſſe ſo euer they haue, in Iuſtice hee reiecteth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Workes of the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate.</note>Now, the workes that are done by the new-borne children of God, ſauour much (though not wholy) of the Spirit of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For they are done with ſome cheerefulneſſe, and willingneſſe, though not with ſuch alacritie, as the godly themſelues wiſh. And this cheerefuleſſe is a thing well pleaſing vnto God, not only in giuing to the reliefe of the needy,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7.</note> but euen in all ſeruice that wee performe to him. When GOD appointed the Tabernacle to bee made, and people were to bring ſtuffe of all ſorts towardes the making thereof, yet might none be accepted vnleſſe it were-giuen <hi>with a willing heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 35.5.21.22. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.108. 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 28 9.</note> And <hi>Dauid</hi> in that reſpect commendeth to God his Prayers: <hi>Accept, O God, the free offerings of my mouth.</hi> And teaching his Sonne how to ſerue God, hee giueth him this leſſon: <hi>And thou, Salomon my Sonne, know thou the God of thy Father, and ſerue him with a perfit heart, and willing mind.</hi> This graced the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes two mites,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.</note> becauſe her willingneſſe of heart, cauſed her to caſt into the treaſurie, that which ſhe could not well ſpare, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as other gaue of their abundance.</p>
            <p>They alſo who are regenerate, ayme as neere as they can, at the right end in their workes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.1.2. The right end of good workes.</note> They doe them not, <hi>that they may be ſeene of men, &amp; prayſed of men,</hi> as do Hypocrits; they reſpect not their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, eſtimation or reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among men, neither haue any other ſuch worldly reſpect in framing themſelues to obedience. No, they ſeeke not thereby to ſatisfie for their ſins as Papiſts doe, moſt iniuriouſly againſt the ſatisfaction that Chriſt hath made, but rather confeſſe that to bee ſpoken to them which <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayth: <hi>Peccata tua maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſunt &amp; nimium multa:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ber. in Cant. Serm. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>nequaquam pro tot &amp; tantis etiamſi te exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, potes ſatisfacere. Thy ſins are very great &amp; very many. Thou canſt not ſatisfie for them being ſo many and ſo great, though thou wouldſt flay off thy skinne.</hi> Their chiefe care in performing their obedience, is <hi>That their light ſo ſhine before men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>that they ſeeing their good workes, may glorifie their Father which is in Heauen.</hi> And although they deſire earneſtly with ſuch alacritie to ſerue GOD: yet find they that moſt truly Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writeth,<note place="margin">Aug. de pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. merit. &amp; remiſſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> alluding to that place of, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Profecto qui de die in diem adhuc renouatur, nondum totus eſt renouatus, &amp; in quantum nondum eſt renouatus, in tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adhuc in vetuſtate eſt. Surely, hee who is yet day by day renued, is not as yet wholly renued, and in aſmuch as hee is not renued, he is of the olde man.</hi> Whereupon he alſo inferreth, <hi>Proinde ex hoc quod in vetustate ſunt,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17908:26"/> quamuis iam baptizati, ex hoc ſunt etiam filij ſeculi. Therefore in as much as they are of the olde man, though they be baptized, yet they are heerein the children of this world.</hi> And what perfit or vnſtained worke, the children of this world are like to doe, it is not hard to geſſe. Seeing therefore, our new birth is heere neuer perfited,<note place="margin">Our new birth he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: not perfit.</note> we cannot ſo apply our ſelues to ſerue God, as that in reſpect of our ſeruice, we dare ſtand as iuſt before God: but with good <hi>Bernard,</hi> we muſt cry; <hi>Meritum meum miſeratio Domini:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ber. in Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. ſer. <hi>61.</hi> Ber. in Pſ. Qui habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat, ſer. <hi>15.</hi> Ber. in Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. ſer. <hi>67.</hi> Auguſt. de Sancta Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginit. c. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>My merit is the Lords mercy. Hoc enim totum eſt hominis meritum, ſi totam ſpem ſuam ponat in eo, qui totum hominem ſaluum fecit? For this is all mans me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, if his whole hope bee only in him, who hath ſaued the whole man.</hi> And, <hi>Deeſt gratiae, quicquid meritis deputas: Whatſoeuer thou giueſt to merit, thou takeſt from grace.</hi> Therefore, with <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alſo wee thinke, that, <hi>Enumerationi meritorum, praefertur confeſſio peccatorum, Confeſſion of ſinnes is better then reckoning of merits.</hi> Out of all which, it is plaine, that according to the worke, is not as the worke meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth (for our workes cannot merit ſo great bleſſing) but according to the nature of the worke: which if it be a fruit of a good Tree, what wanteth in the goodneſſe of the fruit it ſelfe, is in Chriſt ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, in whom we and all that we doe are accepted.</p>
            <p>And the light of this candle, alſo diſcouereth that moſt impious blaſphemie of the Church of Rome againſt God, and their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie againſt men: who theſe many yeeres deceiuing the world, made them beleeue, that the Pope can pardon,<note place="margin">Pardons &amp; Popiſh Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</note> and Prieſts can ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie for mens ſinnes. The gaine that thereby they haue reaped, is verie great (if ſuch wicked getting may be called gaine.) For ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth Pope pardon, nor Prieſts pray, vnleſſe they be wel hired. And whoſoeuer hath ſtore of treaſure, may in that Romiſh Church be bold to ſinne, ſeeing the Pope hath Pardons enow, and Prieſts can patter out heapes of prayers: But woe to poore ſoules that haue no money to buy ſuch merchandize. With ſuch traſh the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures are not acquainted, neyther haue they beene of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny antiquitie, as our Aduerſaries are forced to confeſſe.<note place="margin">Durand. l. <hi>4</hi> diſt. <hi>20.</hi> quaeſt. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Of Pardons we cannot ſay much</hi> (ſayth one of them) <hi>becauſe the Scripture ſpeaketh not expreſly thereof. Iohn Fiſher</hi> our Countrey-man, ſometime Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rocheſter, acknowledgeth that the vſe of Pardons and Purgatorie, <hi>Admodum ſero repertus eſt, is very lately found out.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Artic. <hi>18.</hi> cont. Aſſert. Lutheri.</note> But theſe words vnanſwerably confute that impious doctrine, ſo iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to Chriſt his death and paſſion, <hi>God ſhall reward euery man
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17908:27"/> according to his worke,</hi> I ſay, his worke, <hi>not other mens workes.</hi> For as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>We muſt all appeare before the Iudgement ſeat of Chriſt, that euery man may receiue the things which are done in his body, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that he</hi> (not another) <hi>hath done, whether it be good or euill.</hi> It is therefore a farre more Chriſtian leſſon, to learne out of theſe wordes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10.</note> becauſe <hi>we are Gods workmanſhip, created in Chriſt Ieſus vnto good workes, which God hath ordayned, that wee ſhould walke in them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>while we haue time to doe good vnto all men,</hi> as <hi>S. Paul</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs, and <hi>to paſſe the time of our dwelling here in feare,</hi> as <hi>S. Peter</hi> willeth: then ſo to puffe vp our ſelues with pride of our merits, as if we had ſome good in vs,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7.</note> that <hi>we haue not receiued,</hi> as the Apoſtle vpbraideth the Corinthians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly they obiect</hi> againſt this doctrine of Iuſtification, ſuch Scriptures as promiſe vnto workes eternall life.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 7.14. Promiſe of life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe are they</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>which did come out of great tribulation, and haue waſhed their long robes white in the bloud of the Lambe. Therefore are they in the preſence of the Throne of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34 35.</note> Of this ſort alſo is that: <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdome prepared for you from the beginning of the world: For I was hungry, and yee gaue me meat; I thirſted, and yee gaue me drinke; I was a ſtranger, and yee lodged me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellarm. de Iuſtific. l. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It ſeemeth <hi>Bellarmine</hi> repoſeth in this argument much confidence, as did that great <hi>Goliah</hi> the Philiſtine, in his great ſtrength and mighty weapons. But not euery promiſe of reward, proueth that the thing, whereunto it is ſo promiſed, deſerueth the reward,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.10.</note> which our Aduerſaries are to proue. <hi>Bleſſed are they</hi> (the Truth himſelfe telleth vs) <hi>which ſuffer perſecution for righteouſneſſe ſake, for theirs is the Kingdome of heauen.</hi> And yet the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> counteth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>That the afflictions of this preſent life, are not worthy of the glory which ſhall be ſhewed vnto vs.</hi> Neither doth the Apoſtle take vpon him to controll that, which Chriſt affirmed. For Chriſt ſpeaketh of a reward which ſhall be giuen in mercy: <hi>S. Paul</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, that eternall life cannot be gotten by merits.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.42</note>Likewiſe, <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall giue a cup of cold water only, to one of theſe little ones to drinke in the name of a Diſciple, verily, I ſay vnto you, hee ſhall not leeſe his reward.</hi> Vpon which wordes the Author of the vnperfect worke in <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Author o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perf. hom. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> writeth thus: <hi>Non quia ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid eſt quod dat, habet mercedem, ſed quia magnus est propter quem dat: He hath his reward, not becauſe it is any thing that he giueth, but becauſe hee is great for whoſe ſake hee giueth it.</hi> And <hi>Leo</hi> a Pope,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17908:27"/> handling the ſame wordes too, yeeldeth this reaſon, why a cup of cold water, a thing of it ſelfe very meane, ſhould haue promiſe of reward, ſaith thus: <hi>Quae per ſe vilsa ſunt, fides efficit pretioſa:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leo ſerm. <hi>6.</hi> de quadrag. ſimile ſer. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; de itiun. ſer. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Things baſe of themſelues, faith maketh precious.</hi> But to this end, that which before I ſpoke of the workes of the regenerate tendeth. For let a man, not regenerate, offer many times of (I ſay not cold water) but of moſt precious liquor, to what vſe, or to whom he will; yet cannot he hope for any reward in heauen. For it is faith that puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth our hearts, and alſo teacheth vs to depend vpon the goodnes of God, framing our hearts vnto obedience, and ſeaſoneth our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frings and all that we doe. It is faith, I ſay, that taking hold of the promiſes, looketh in all our workes, not what we doe, but what God promiſeth.<note place="margin">August. in Pſal. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non aliquid Deo dedimus &amp; debitorem tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Vnde debitorem? quia promiſſor eſt. Non dicimus Deo, Redde quod accepisti, ſed, Redde quod promiſiſti: We gaue nothing to God, and he is become our debter. How is he our debter? Becauſe he is a promiſer. We ſay not to God, Reſtore what thou haſt receiued, but, Pay that thou haſt promiſed.</hi> And againe, <hi>Fidelis Deus, qui ſe nobis fecit debitorem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. <hi>109.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non aliquid à nobis accipiendo, ſed tanta promittendo: God is faithfull who hath made himſelfe our debter, not in taking any thing of vs, but in promiſing ſo great things to vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee therefore confeſſe, that eternall life is a reward giuen to good workes, but not in reſpect of the merit of the worke, but in regard of the promiſe, which he that is faithfull hath made. A ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant is hyred to doe his Maſters worke, hee agreeth of his wages, and taketh the worke in hand. But his Maſter oft findeth fault with his negligence, want of skill to worke as he ſhould, or other wants, whereby his worke he findeth not well done, which he alſo might, if he would, alleage, as not being bound to pay for that is not done, or is euill done. Yet his Maſter payeth him that he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed; not becauſe his worke deſerued the wages, but becauſe he promiſed him ſo much, and was not willing to remember all the faults, that were in the worke. Euen ſo is it with the beſt ſeruants that God hath. Our ſeruice is farre ſhort of that it ſhould be: yet God, for Chriſt his ſake, pardoneth our wants, accepteth our good indeuours, and becauſe he is faithfull, is as good as his word and promiſe to vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A fourth obiection</hi> they haue, out of ſuch places as teſtifie of the innocency of Gods ſeruants. And <hi>they are of two ſorts.</hi> For the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17908:28"/> Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> doth very often by that argument craue aide of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 7.8.</note> becauſe of his innocency and righteouſneſſe. <hi>Iudge thou me, O Lord,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>according to my righteouſneſſe, and according to the innocency that is in me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.21.</note> Againe, <hi>Let my vprightneſſe and equitie preſerue me.</hi> Whoſo readeth the booke of Pſalmes, ſhall find this very common.<note place="margin">Innocent herein, not ſimply</note> But out of ſuch prayers, no man may conclude, that <hi>Dauid</hi> pleadeth righteouſnes before God, or merit of works. He only alleageth, that in this point he was righteous, that he had giuen no iuſt cauſe to them, why they ſhould ſo perſecute and purſue him, and ſeeke his life. Therefore hee complayneth, that <hi>they hate him without a cauſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 35.19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.4.</note> 
               <hi>and make him reſtore the thing hee neuer tooke.</hi> Infinite ſuch places are in Scripture, whereby it plainely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, what innocency or righteouſneſſe the Prophet ſpeaketh of. Not that he is iuſt before God: but that men deale vniuſtly with him. And this is no good argument: <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, he is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in reſpect of his aduerſaries malice againſt him: therefore he pleadeth his iuſtice before God himſelfe, or that he is ſimply or altogether righteous.</p>
            <p>But ſometime alſo righteouſneſſe is aſcribed vnto men here vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth. As among ſundry other to <hi>Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of whom <hi>S. Luke</hi> writeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.6. Innocent, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> 
               <hi>Both were iuſt before God, and walked in all the Commandements and Ordinances of the Lord, without reproofe. S. Auguſtine</hi> handling this very hiſtory, doth truly teach what iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice they had, as elſewhere, ſo namely in theſe wordes: <hi>Secundum quandam inter homines conuerſationem laudabilem &amp; probabilem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. cont. Pelag. &amp; Celeſtin. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quam nullus hominum poſſet iuſtè in quaerelam vocare: They were iuſt in regard of their conuerſation, commendable and allowable, ſuch as no man might iuſtly complaine of.</hi> And after hee bringeth the example of <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil</hi> 3.6.</note> who <hi>according to the righteouſneſſe that was by the Law, was without reproofe.</hi> And yet this righteouſneſſe he accounted dung, and loſſe, <hi>In compariſon</hi> (ſaith AVG.) <hi>of that which he hoped for.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe the Pelagians preſſed him with an authority out of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> to proue that a man might in this life be perfit, he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what minde <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> was of for that point, alleaging ſome words of his out of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his Commentaries vpon <hi>Eſay,</hi> which booke is not now extant (that I haue ſeene) although here and elſewhere, <hi>S. Aug.</hi> make mention thereof. And <hi>Ambroſe</hi> himſelfe referreth vs alſo to that booke;<note place="margin">Amb. in Luc lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> The wordes alleaged are theſe, <hi>Multi ſunt perfecti in hoc mundo, qui ſi perfectionem veram reſpicias,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:17908:28"/> perfecti eſſe non poſſunt: Many are perfit in this world, who if you looke to true perfection, cannot be perfit.</hi> Whereupon alſo <hi>S. Auguſt.</hi> doth thus conclude, <hi>Item immaculati ſunt multi, quum ſi minutiùs excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as, immaculatus eſſe nemo poſſit, quiae nemo ſine peccato: Many alſo are vndefiled, when as if you ſift the matter narrowly, no man can be vndefiled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notably alſo for this point writeth <hi>S. Ambroſe,</hi> by occaſion of thoſe wordes of the Apoſtle. <hi>Let vs as many as bee perfit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>bee thus minded;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. in Ep. ad Phil. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ad comparationem caeterorum qui res diuinas negligentiùs curant, perfecti dicendi ſunt, qui adhibita ſolertia perfectionis it er am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulant: In compariſon</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of ſuch as are negligent in heauenly matters, they may be called perfect, who are carefull to walke in the wayes of perfection.</hi> S. BASIL expounding theſe wordes of the Prophet DAVID, <hi>Iudge me, O Lord, according to my righteouſnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſil. in Pſal. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and according to my innocency that is in me,</hi> taketh innocency to bee ſimplicity, or <hi>want of experience,</hi> whereby men fall into many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences: And righteouſneſſe hee interpreteth to be ſuch iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, as is <hi>hominibus comprehenſibilis, &amp; poſſibilis his qui in carne vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uunt: Such as men may attaine to, and is poſſible for them to haue who liue in the fleſh:</hi> and thus he frameth that prayer: <hi>Ad librilem hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae fragilitatis iuſtitiam meam appendens, ita me iudices: Waighing my righteouſneſſe in the wayſcales of mans frailty, iudge me after that manner.</hi> By all this it doth appeare, that though ſome are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in Scriptures as iuſt men: yet perfect righteouſnes (which only can ſtand before God) none can attaine vnto. For,<note place="margin">Hier. cont. Pelag. l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cunctorum in carne iuſtorum imperfecta iuſtitia eſt: The perfection euen of all iust men, while they are in the fleſh, is vnperfit,</hi> as <hi>S. Hierome</hi> ſaith: but vnperfect righteouſneſſe cannot merit eternall life: therefore no perfection that man hath here, can merit that life.</p>
            <p>This, which I haue already ſaid, I would haue thought a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient anſwere to thoſe Scriptures, wherein ſome are commended as iuſt: but ſeeing ſome contend to eſtabliſh a greater righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in vs, then we can haue, I am forced a little further to looke into this matter. <hi>Kemnitius,</hi> a great learned man,<note place="margin">Popiſh im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Merits. <hi>Kem. exam. part.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 211.</note> who hath moſt learnedly examined thoſe wicked decrees of the impious Councel of Trent, telleth vs, that <hi>Lindan,</hi> no ſmall foole in the Romiſh Church (<hi>Reuerendiſs. Epiſcopus Traiectenſis,</hi> he is called) is very angry with ſome of his fellowes, for affirming, that <hi>God of his cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency and goodneſſe rewardeth our good works,</hi> to which he teacheth
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:17908:29"/> a reward to be due for the worthineſſe thereof. <hi>Andradius Paiuas,</hi> I am ſure,<note place="margin">Andrad. Orthod. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicat. lib <hi>6.</hi> pag. <hi>518.</hi>
               </note> dareth and ſhameth not to write, that <hi>the ioy of heauen, which the Scripture calleth the retribution and reward of the righteous, is not ſo much giuen them of God freely and liberally, as it is due to their workes.</hi> And as the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> proueth our Iuſtification by grace,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.4.</note> becauſe otherwiſe it ſhould rather bee of debt then of fauour (and <hi>the reward and grace,</hi> ſaith he, are quite contrary) ſo dareth this man (becauſe eternall life is in Scripture called a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) gather this doctrine moſt falſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 519. <hi>Pag.</hi> 522.</note> 
               <hi>That it ought not to be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted according to grace, but as a debt.</hi> And not long after he repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth <hi>Kemnitius,</hi> for finding fault with the Cenſurers of Colen, for writing <hi>that God ſet on ſale eternall life.</hi> And not much vnlike is that,<note place="margin">Cenſ. Colon. explicat. Dialog. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> which they of Colen teach, <hi>That by grace there is in our works an infiniteneſſe, that they being ſomewhat holpen by that gift</hi> (of grace) <hi>doe worthily merit eternal life.</hi> So that we ſee, they imagine, any lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle helpe will ſerue the turne: A plaine proofe, that their ſtudie was more how to defend their doctrine, then in ſinceritie to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine themſelues, how vnable they are to keepe Gods Law, ſo as they may merit eternall life thereby.</p>
            <p>A man may iuſtly wonder, how any that hath any feeling of his owne frailty, or any knowledge of Gods word, can bee ſo beſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as to teach that which is ſo contrary to that euery one of vs doe, or iuſtly may feele in our ſelues, and ſo directly againſt moſt manifeſt Scriptures. Is any of them better then he, who ſaid, no doubt as well in reſpect of himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 15.14.</note> as of others, <hi>What is man that he ſhould be cleane? and he that is borne of a woman, that he ſhould be iuſt?</hi> Are they more righteous then <hi>Dauid,</hi> who confeſſeth, that <hi>if God enter into iudgement with his ſeruants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.2.</note> 
               <hi>no fleſh liuing ſhall be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, or found righteous in his ſight?</hi> Are they holier then he, who ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.5.</note> 
               <hi>We haue ſinned, and haue committed iniquity, and done wickedly, yea, we haue rebelled and haue departed from thy precepts, and from thy iudgements?</hi> Are they of greater power to reſiſt ſinne, then <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.19.</note> 
               <hi>I doe not the good thing that I would, and the euill which I would not, that doe I?</hi> I thinke, they dare not for very ſhame, to match themſelues with theſe men, that had ſo great teſtimonie of their ſincerity from God himſelfe; at the leaſt they will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre themſelues. How then dare they ſo ſtand vpon their merits, ſeeing theſe godly men haue no truſt in their works, but ſo wholy diſable them?</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:17908:29"/>
            <p>Neyther is there in the Scripture any thing more plainly deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, any Doctrine more often taught,<note place="margin">Scriptures are againſt doctrine of merits. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.</note> then that which teacheth vs to deny our merits, and to reſt only vpon Gods mercy in Chriſt for the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes. <hi>Not by the workes of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which we haue done</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) but according to his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies he ſaued vs.</hi> And againe, <hi>God hath ſaued vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>and called vs with a holy calling, not according to our workes, but according to his owne purpoſe and grace, which was giuen to vs through Chriſt Ieſus before the world was.</hi> And againe, <hi>By grace ye are ſaued, through faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>and that not of your ſelues, it is the gift of God, not of workes, leſt any ſhould boaſt himſelfe.</hi> And infinite teſtimonies tending to this end (if it were needfull) might be brought, prouing plainly how little we may reſt vpon our merits, and how little ſoundnes is in our workes, and therefore alſo ſhewing how little cauſe our aduerſaries haue to write that eternall life is due to good workes not of mercy, but of merit, as LINDAN, ANDRADIVS, and the Colen Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers doe teach.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of this conceit they haue of their workes, is becauſe they ſuppoſe none but great ſinnes hinder our perfection. <hi>Leuicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la vitiola (Kemnitius</hi> alleageth out of <hi>Lindan</hi> a Popiſh Biſhop) <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpergines &amp; naeuuli ſunt, qui perſe non maculant nec contaminant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kem. exam. part.</hi> 1. Veniall ſins they lightly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme.</note> 
               <hi>ſed quaſi puluiſculo leuiter aspergunt vitam Christianam, vt nihilominùs tamen per ſe ſint perfecta, &amp; vndique immaculata renatorum opera in hac vita.</hi> Which, if they bee the words of <hi>Lindan,</hi> hee vſeth ſo many diminitiues to leſſen and make nothing our breach of Gods Law, as thereby he ſheweth himſelfe to be a very graceles wretch, without any feeling of the burden of ſinne. They are in Engliſh thus: <hi>Little, light, petty ſinnes, are as ſprinklings and ſmall ſtaines, which doe not of themſelues blot or defile, but as it were with ſmall dust, doe lightly ſprinkle a Chriſtian life, ſo as, notwithstanding the workes of the regenerate, are of themſelues perfect, and euery way vndefiled.</hi> Indeed, <hi>Andradius</hi> too, though not in ſuch ſcornfull termes (as I may well call them) teacheth the like Doctrine:<note place="margin">Andra. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicat. l. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Peccata</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in quae iusti quotidie labuntur, iustitiam euertere nullo pacto poſſunt, ac proinde neque perfectam &amp; abſolutam legis obedientiam quoquo modo impedire: The ſinnes whereinto euen the iust daily fall, can by no meanes ouerthrow righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cenſ. Colon. explicat. er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorum Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logi. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and therefore cannot any thing hinder the full and perfit obedience of the Law.</hi> The Cenſurers of Colen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, though not ſo vnmodeſtly, yet as vntruly as <hi>Lindan,</hi> affirme,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:17908:30"/> ſpeaking of veniall ſins, that <hi>Leuia illa nec impios, nec malos efficiunt, nec operum noſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum obſunt efficaciae; Thoſe light ſinnes make men ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wicked nor euill, neyther doe they hinder the efficacie of their workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which their Doctrine, to bee moſt abſurd and falſe, wee may proue by many reaſons,<note place="margin">The leaſt ſinnes hinder our obedience and ſtaine it.</note> as firſt thus. Euery breach of Gods Law maketh our obedience vnperfit: but euery veniall ſinne is a breach of Gods Law, therefore euery veniall ſinne maketh our obedience vnperfit. My <hi>Maior</hi> I would thinke ſhould need no proofe ſeeing that where breach of a Law is, there is not abſolute obedience to the ſame. And Saint <hi>Iames</hi> telleth vs, <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall keepe the whole Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>and yet faileth in one point, hee is guilty of all.</hi> But that euery veniall ſinne is a breach of Gods Law, is plaine. For if there be no breach of Law, then is not forgiueneſſe needfull: but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe is needfull for the taking away of veniall ſinnes, as is moſt manifeſt by that place of Saint <hi>Iohn: If wee acknowledge our ſinnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.8.9</note> 
               <hi>he is faithfull to forgiue vs our ſinnes, and to clenſe vs from all vnrighteouſneſſe.</hi> Whereby we vnderſtand that the ſinnes that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh of, are by forgiueneſſe to bee done away. And that he ſpeaketh of veniall ſinnes, not only <hi>Andradius, Paiuas</hi> doth teſtifie,<note place="margin">Andro. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicat. lib. <hi>5.</hi> pag. <hi>421.</hi> Bell. de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſ. grat. l. <hi>1</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> but <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alſo in plaine words. So that by two wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of good credit among our Aduerſaries, it appeareth, that veniall ſinnes are no otherwiſe taken away then other ſinnes are, and therefore that our perfit obedience is by them ſo hindered, as that it cannot ſtand before the iuſt Iudge.</p>
            <p>Againe, whatſoeuer ſinnes are ſhort of that obedience that God commandeth in this Law, <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>with all thy ſoule, with all thy might:</hi> are hinderances vnto the perfection of obedience: but the ſinnes which they call venial doe that (for in committing of them our whole heart, minde and ſoule is not bent to obſerue Gods Law) therefore ſuch ſinnes are a hinderance to our perfit keeping of the Law. But to be ſhort: If veniall ſinnes be no tranſgreſſion of Law, they are to be much blamed that call them ſinnes: <hi>(For where there is no Law, there is no tranſgreſſion)</hi> but if they bee a breach of Law, as before I ſaid, they are of the nature of ſinnes, and vnleſſe they be pardoned, ſhall alſo haue the reward of ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The godly feare their venial ſins.</note>But what ſeeke I to proue that, which euery mans owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience (if they be not too much beſotted) will tell them? Was it not veniall ſinnes as our Aduerſaries account, that made <hi>Paul</hi> cry
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:17908:30"/> out as he doth: <hi>O wretched man that I am,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24.</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall deliuer me from the bodie of this death?</hi> He could neuer haue ſaid of himſelfe as he doth, of being without reproofe concerning the Law, if he had beene ſtained with notorious and ſuch as they call mortall ſinnes. And ſhall <hi>Paul</hi> be ſo ſcarred with veniall ſinnes, and can wee ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine they make vs nothing the worſe? How much better were it for vs with good <hi>Bernard</hi> to confeſſe: <hi>Paſſio tua vltimum refugium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ber. in Can. Ser. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſingulare remedium. Deficiente ſapientia, iustitia non ſufficiente, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbentibus ſanctitatis meritis illa ſuccurrit. O Lord, thy paſſion is my laſt refuge, a ſingular remedy. For when wiſdome wanteth, Iuſtice ſufficeth not, and merits of holineſſe faile, that helpeth.</hi> And thus I truſt it doth appeare, that howſoeuer our Aduerſaries teach of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall ſinnes (which they confeſſe are in the godly) yet are they ſuch ſtaines in the garment of our righteouſneſſe, as are not to bee ſhaken off with euery knocke of the breſt, or waſhed off, with ſprinkling a little holy-water or other ſuch like tryfling deuices. No, no: vnleſſe this our garment be dipt in the bloud of Chriſt and ſo made white, it will euer appeare defiled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A fift obiection.</hi> They tell vs that eternall life is called a reward, <hi>great is your reward in Heauen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.12.</note> As before in anſwering their third obiection, I ſayd, that not euery promiſe proueth that which is giuen, to be merited by the worke: ſo heere I doe auerre,<note place="margin">How life eternall is called a reward.</note> that the calling of eternall life a reward, doth not euict, that it is giuen in regard of the worthineſſe of the worke. If you demand, why it is then called a reward: I anſwere, It pleaſeth God not only to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint vs with his will, that we may know what is good and what is euil: but alſo by many arguments ſometime of his power, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time of his Iuſtice, ſometime of his goodneſſe to moue his people to obedience. To them therefore, that with more alacritie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>While we haue time to do good vnto all men,</hi> as the Apoſtle exhorteth, he telleth vs that our labour ſhall not be without reward. The like argument doth the Apoſtle vſe to the Corinthians,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Co.</hi> 15.58</note> 
               <hi>Therefore my beloued bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, be yee ſtedfaſt, vnmoueable, abundant alwayes in the worke of the Lord, knowing that your labour is not in vaine in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But eternall life is called a reward: Be it ſo. It is alſo called a Kingdome,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34</note> and that prepared for Gods ſeruants <hi>from the beginning of the world.</hi> If prepared ſo long ſince for them, then not beſtowed for the worthineſſe of their worke. If a Kingdome, it is an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that is giuen by grace (for we are ſonnes by adoption) <hi>heires
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:17908:31"/> of God, and heires annexed with Christ.</hi> Or elſe by election we haue this inheritance.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17.</note> For no man is elected to a Kengdome in regard of his merits, eſpecially, ſo long before hee can doe any thing for it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſſ</hi> 3.24.</note> The Apoſtle calleth it a reward of inheritance. <hi>Ye ſhall receiue a reward of inheritance</hi> (ſayth he.)</p>
            <p>Howſoeuer, therefore it is called ſometime a reward, yet is it a reward that is promiſed,<note place="margin">Gal. <hi>3.29.</hi> Bel. de Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> and therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, <hi>Wee are heires by promiſe.</hi> And therefore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe confeſſeth, <hi>that remota promiſſione, non tenetur Deus acceptare opus noſtrum ad mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedem: taking away the promiſe, God is not bound to accept our worke, to reward it.</hi> Now if a father promiſe his ſonne, being yet but a childe both in ſtrength and diſcretion (and ſuch children are we in heauenly matters) a great reward, if hee doe ſome ſmall matter at his appointment, yet ſuch as hee knoweth paſſeth eyther his abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie or skill: whether ſhall we ſay when this recompence is giuen, that it is of promiſe or of dutie? The ſonne indeuoureth as well as he can to doe it, and with much adoe with continuall helpe of his father, he doth it at length in ſome ſort. I hope no man will ſay his worke deſerued it. For the Father promiſed much for a ſmall matter, hee helpeth his ſonne to doe it, and beareth in the end with many wants: euen ſo God for the little that wee can doe promiſeth much, and that wee doe hath many imperfections too. Can wee then thinke of merit?<note place="margin">Ber in Cant. Serm. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</hi>
               </note> No, no, <hi>the Spouſe of Chriſt doth then ſhew her ſelfe to be more full of grace, when ſhe aſcribeth all to grace, knowing her part is firſt and last.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.7.</note>But againſt the meriting of the reward, that parable in S. <hi>Luke</hi> is moſt plaine. A ſeruant ploweth, or doth any other worke in the field, when hee commeth home, his Maſter biddeth him not ſit downe, but willeth him to dreſſe meat, and giue himſelfe, and wait and ſerue him: teaching vs that we haue no time to beſtow other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then vpon our Maſters worke.<note place="margin">Ambroſ. in Luke <hi>17.</hi> Theopilact. in Luk. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>We muſt alwayes while wee liue be doing,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ambroſe. This Parable ſheweth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Theophilact) that a man muſt not be proud of any good worke: no, neyther yet in the fulfilling of all the Commandements. For the ſeruant muſt doe what his Master commandeth, neither muſt hee aſcribe it to himſelfe as a good worke.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. in Luk. <hi>7.</hi> Dioniſ. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſ. in Luk. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Ambroſe</hi> gathereth the ſame leſſon too. <hi>Let no man glory of workes, for we owe our ſeruice to the Lord.</hi> So doth the <hi>Carthuſian</hi> alſo. <hi>The ſeruant is tyed to this, and after his worke in the field, he muſt labour in the houſe that he may daily be labouring.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:17908:31"/>
            <p>It being thus, let vs conſider of the concluſion of the Parable. <hi>So likewiſe ye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.10.</note> 
               <hi>when you haue done all things which were commanded you, ſay, We are vnprofitable ſeruants, we haue done that was our dutie to doe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hieron. ad Cteſiphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. Theophil. in Luk.</hi> 17. No merit in this worke.</note> 
               <hi>If that ſeruant were vnprofitable that did all</hi> (ſayth <hi>Hierom) What ſhall we ſay of him that could not doe it? Theophilact</hi> alſo in like manner. <hi>If when we haue done all the Commandements, yet wee haue no cauſe to thinke well of our doing, how greatly doe we ſinne, when not doing the greateſt part of Gods Commandements; yet we are proud of our doing?</hi> The <hi>Carthuſian</hi> likewiſe: <hi>If they must account them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnprofitable ſeruants, who haue fulfilled all the Commandements: what ſhall we doe, who in ſo many things tranſgreſſe, and ſo vnperfectly perchance keepe that we keepe, that as the Prophet</hi> Eſai <hi>ſayth, all our righteouſneſſe is like a filthy clout?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Bellarmine</hi> telleth vs,<note place="margin">De Iuſtific. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> Bernard. de tripl. cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia. Bernard. de precepto &amp; diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</note> that Chriſt ſo concludeth to teach hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie. I anſwere with <hi>Bernard, Sanè propter humilitatem, ſed num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid contra veritatem? True indeed for humility: but is it againſt verity?</hi> He alſo elſewhere thus ſpeaketh to that ſeruant: <hi>You are free from duty, but not glorious by merit: You haue eſcaped puniſhment, but haue not gotten the crowne.</hi> The Parable teacheth vs, that all wee can doe is dutie, therefore wee may not thinke of merit: becauſe, whatſoeuer wee are able to performe at any time, in any place, by any meanes, we owe all that ſeruice to God.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I come to thoſe words of <hi>Iames,</hi> in ſhew as contrarie to Saint <hi>Paul</hi> as can be; yet becauſe they both had one teacher, both were guided in writing by one Spirit, and were both of one faith and Religion, we are ſure both teach one Doctrine.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.24. What Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is by workes. <hi>Iude</hi> 4. <hi>Aug lib.</hi> 83. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 76. <hi>&amp; de fide &amp; operibus cap.</hi> 14.</note> And yet <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, <hi>We are iuſtified by faith without workes. Iames</hi> ſayth, <hi>Wee are iuſtified by workes, and not by faith only:</hi> and both theſe are moſt true. For if we ſpeake of the cauſe of Iuſtification, then muſt wee hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who teacheth, that is by faith without workes. But, becauſe many <hi>turning the grace of God into wantonneſſe,</hi> gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the Apoſtles words that ſo they beleeued, they needed no regard or care how they liued, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith in moe places then one: Therefore Saint <hi>Iames</hi> teacheth, how men ſhall know that wee are iuſtified, and what manner of faith this true faith is. For faith without workes as it is not a true, or liuing, but a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit and dead faith, ſo it auaileth nothing to Iuſtification.</p>
            <p>So that <hi>the word of Iuſtification</hi> hath not the like ſignification in <hi>S. Iames,</hi> that it had in <hi>S. Paul.</hi> For in <hi>S. Paul</hi> it is taken for our
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:17908:32"/> iuſtification before God, as in the beginning I haue declared plentifully. And in <hi>S. Iames</hi> it ſignifieth that Iuſtification before men, whereby we are knowne to be righteous. <hi>S. Iames</hi> his words tend to that end:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>Shew me thy faith by thy workes, and I will ſhew thee my faith by my workes.</hi> He would haue a faith ſhewed to men, which cannot be but by workes: for works are the touchſtone, whereby a true and liuely faith is diſcerned from a falſe and dead faith, when oportuniry is offered to vs, to bring forth that fruit. Otherwiſe the faith that many ſpeake of, will proue no better, ſcarſe ſo good,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19.</note> as that <hi>the Deuils haue, who beleeue and tremble.</hi> Therefore as <hi>S. Peter</hi> exhorteth vs to beautifie our ſelues, with that better then any golden chaine of Chriſtian vertues, which will <hi>make vs neither idle nor vnfruitfull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>in the knowledge of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> ſo doth S. <hi>Iames</hi> giue them of his time to vnderſtand, how they haue miſtaken a bare name of faith and knowledge of Chriſt, for an effectuall and a iuſtifying faith.</p>
            <p>He therefore ſpeaketh in this ſort: Thou ſaiſt thou haſt faith: I ſee it not, for thy workes ſhew no ſuch matter. Proue then before men that thou haſt this confidence in God, that thou haſt this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance within thee, of thy atonement with him. <hi>Primaſius</hi> who wrote about 1100. yeeres ſince, ſo expoundeth theſe wordes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling that which ſeemed to bee contradiction in the Apoſtles S. <hi>Iames</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſpeaketh of the workes that ſhew a man to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Primaſ. in Rom. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>as himſelfe in that which followeth, expoundeth it: Shew me by workes thy faith. It is workes whereby faith is knowne.</hi> Venerable <hi>Bede</hi> alſo is of that minde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bede</hi> vpon <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.</note> that <hi>Iames</hi> would <hi>vt fidem ſuam per ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra probarent: That they ſhould proue their faith by their workes.</hi> But <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Aquine</hi> the Angellicall Doctor, whoſe authority in the Romiſh Church will beare the ſway, will looſe this knot. For re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling thoſe wordes of PAVL.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>No man is iuſtified by the Law,</hi> with theſe wordes of <hi>Iames,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.21.</note> ABRAHAM <hi>was iuſtified by workes:</hi> He telleth that the iuſtification that is of workes, is an execution or manifeſtation of righteouſneſſe, whereby he <hi>is ſhewed to be iuſt.</hi> And, by and by after: <hi>The righteouſneſſe before God is in the inner heart:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tho. Aquin. in Gal. <hi>3.</hi> Lect. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but the righteouſnes that is of workes, that is that maketh knowne or manifeſt him that is iuſt: is before men.</hi> What can be ſpoken more plaine? S. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth how with boldnes we may ſtand before God, pleading not guilty (now this confidence is alwayes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vs) S. <hi>Iames</hi> would haue this by their fruit to appeare vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:17908:32"/> 
               <hi>Leſt men deceiue their owne hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.26.</note> 
               <hi>and the Religion of ſuch men proue vaine,</hi> as himſelfe ſaith elſewhere. Thus then truly conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, in what ſenſe the one and the other Apoſtle doe take the word <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> the difference appeareth to be none at all, and ſo the matter is eaſily compounded.</p>
            <p>And thus I truſt it will appeare, the premiſes truly conſidered, that our interpretation of the Apoſtles wordes, <hi>(A man is iuſtified by faith without the workes of the Law)</hi> is both true and Catholike:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28.</note> our concluſion, that out of them we gather is ſound, and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Apoſtles doctrine, hauing a very great conſent of moſt approued antiquitie, yea and of Popiſh writers too: And our workes (how good ſoeuer) haue not in them any worthineſſe or merit, but are in mercy rewarded according to promiſe. So that the ſeruant of God muſt learne with good <hi>Bernard,</hi> to ſay;<note place="margin">Bern. ſuper Cantic. ſer. <hi>67.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gratia reddit me mihi iuſtificatum gratis, &amp; ſic liberatum a ſeruitute pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti: Grace reſtoreth me to my ſelfe iuſtified freely, and ſo deliuered from the thraldome of ſinne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.23.24.</note> Then ſhall we <hi>ſing with that multitude of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Souldiers prayſing God and ſaying, Glory be to God on high.</hi> Yea with thoſe <hi>many Angels round about the Throne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel</hi> 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>and about the Beaſts and the Elders, and thoſe thouſand thouſands, Saying with a lowd voice: Worthy is the Lambe that was killed, to receiue power, and riches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">12.</note> 
               <hi>and wiſedome, and ſtrength, and honor, and glory, and prayſe:</hi> becauſe, O Lord, <hi>Thou haſt redeemed vs to God by thy bloud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">9. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>yea thou haſt loued vs, and in it haſt waſhed vs from our ſinnes.</hi> Which Meditations will teach vs, caſting off all confidence in our ſelues, or our owne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iob.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21.</note> to reſt only vpon him <hi>that came to deſtroy the workes of the Deuill, and to ſaue his people from their ſinnes: who his owne ſelfe bare our ſinnes in his body vpon the tree, that we being deliuered from ſinne, ſhould liue in righteouſneſſe: by whoſe ſtripes we are healed.</hi> To him therefore with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, bee all honor and praiſe, now and euer. AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
